<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://heartsoulmachine.com/">
  <title>Heart Soul Machine</title>
  <subtitle>Posts from the blog of Tim Klapdor.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2024-08-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Tim Klapdor</name>
    <email>tim.klapdor@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>July 2024</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/08-04-july-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-08-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/08-04-july-2024/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The Vibe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;July just flew by. Probably because a lot happened during the month that&#39;s kept things busy. Ms A was away for a week visiting family during the school holidays, and the dog had a week at the kennels, so there were a couple of &amp;quot;quieter&amp;quot; weeks during the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My walking regime has been OK, but the gym completely fell of this month. I need to reconfigure my routine during August so that I am prioritising this time and burn off of calories. I think it would do my mental health wonders, but as always, these are always the hardest things to do when you&#39;re in a funk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work.... I don&#39;t think things have gotten any better. My complaint is the lack of planning or organisation regarding the work that needs to be done. I&#39;ve tried to intervene positively and prompt basic things like to-do lists and schedules to be developed and time put aside to collaborate, but nothing happened in that space. I think that&#39;s the end of me trying to change anything now. I have to draw a line when it comes to wasted effort, and that&#39;s now. There is no point in continuing to try and affect any change - there is absolutely no appetite for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is set, and there is no turning back now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I am concerned about the effect this will have on my team and all the other personnel involved. No one seems to give a fuck anymore from a practical capacity about work and welfare. Sure, they say all the right words in public, but the reality is that every decision undermines trust, refuses to acknowledge any of the realities of being a human (getting sick, being tired, stressed and overwhelmed) and diminishes the key structures that allow people to remain resilient - the team and the people around them. Rather than seeking to build up the existing support structures, the focus is on some theoretical notion of leadership and teams that are so far removed from any practical reality you can tell that only people who lack any experience in this area could have thought it up. And rather than utilising the skill and experience at their fingertips, and against all advice they keep returning to their imagined reality as the way things will get done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well my big event for July was my 44th Birthday. Unlike previous years, we did plan a bit of a celebration and a night out with friends feasting at Peel St and an after-dinner cocktail at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibliotheca.com.au/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Bibliotheca&lt;/a&gt;.  I also had a couple of pints of Kilkenny and a Chinese meal at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://brecknock.weebly.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Brecknock Hotel Corner Bar&lt;/a&gt; - an old pub that&#39;s been divided into a cozy homestyle Irish bar in the small front bar and a massive Chinese restaurant in the rest of the building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The week after the biggest thing to happen to our home started - the kitchen renovations. Having dreamt this up almost as soon as we moved in, after about 3 years, we&#39;re finally underway... slowly. The unique angles in the house obviously played havoc for the cabinet makers during the installation, and we&#39;re now stuck without a viable kitchen as all the other dependencies kick in. We currently have cabinets in and benchtop templates ready to go to the stainless steel fabricators, but that&#39;s it. There&#39;s no more forward momentum until the benches are in, so no usable kitchen. &lt;code&gt;¯&#92;_(ツ)_/¯ &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a week of ongoing dramas with the installation - missing elements like taps and sink, new fridge not fitting through the doorway without requiring pin-point manoeuvring to get into the house and a few &amp;quot;hold my beer moments&amp;quot; with the other appliances. I think we&#39;re on track now, but it is a bit of a wait-and-see when it will actually be finished, so at the moment, the house is a mess, there are no usable benches for meal prep, and it&#39;s not fun attempting to cook anything at this point in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also spoke at the TALAS Symposium - an opportunity to share practice and ideas with our UniSA colleagues. It was a good opportunity for me to share the work around Learning Types and Patterns that I&#39;ve been doing in the background. It also gave me the impetus to pull together a revamp of the Learning Patterns website. It&#39;s not 100% public (but if you &lt;a href=&quot;https://learning-patterns.com/test-index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;know where to look&lt;/a&gt;) it&#39;s up online so I can do some testing with it. I&#39;ve updated the CSS, now have a dark mode, and swapped out the entire site to be a single page with details popping up using the new Popover API! I&#39;m super happy as it&#39;s performant, works with Translation features and has almost zero javascript. Hopefully, pulling all of this into the public-facing version soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time as all of this is going on there are snippets of joy. There was a koala in our yard one morning! One of my best friends is moving to Adelaide! We climbed a hill and had an amazing view of a pod of dolphins frolicking in the bay! And the sunrises and sunsets have been spectacular - and I&#39;m awake to see them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ooops - I forgot about June photos so added them to the Flickr album too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/timklapdor/albums/72177720314386151&quot; title=&quot;2024&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53899609967_3e8b509ea9_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;2024&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Watched&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a bit of a stroll down memory lane with &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.imdb.com/title/tt3083016/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Axel F&lt;/a&gt;. The next season of &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.imdb.com/title/tt11311302/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Vikings Valhalla&lt;/a&gt;, which I like but it never quite gets me that into the story - I think maybe its the character switching - each of the stories are interesting, but you&#39;re constantly switching between story arcs. Also finished off the Boys and The Acolyte - both underwhelming but entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Listened&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some great podcasts I made my way through during July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both seasons of Ultra by Rachel Maddow - a really great and unknown story for me about the rightwing, and literal Nazis in American politics. So good and poignant and ultimately human story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I smashed through season 2 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/m001hf1w&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Buried&lt;/a&gt;. I love the story but hate the episode length. So frustrating that when you&#39;re finally getting into it and it ends, and then theres a couple of minutes of credits, ads and preroll. This season is on PCB contamination and the unlikely hero, Douglas Gowan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also went through  S04 &amp;amp; S05 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/gb/podcast/cover-up-the-conspiracy-tapes/id1621750804&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Cover Up&lt;/a&gt;, The Anthrax Threat and The Conspiracy Tapes. The Anthrax Treat was quite eye-opening in how wide-reaching and large-scale that attack was and that so many people died. The Conspiracy Tapes was something else, quite Jon Ronson in the sense of it going back and tugging on the threads back to the source of so much of the conspiracy theory culture that exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also finally got around to finishing up Scene on Radio&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://sceneonradio.org/seeing-white/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Seeing White&lt;/a&gt; season. I got a huge amount out of this series and thoroughly recommend it as &lt;strong&gt;one of the best explorations of race&lt;/strong&gt; out there. While the context is American, so much of the concept of &#39;whiteness&#39; resonates here in Australian society. A country that had a literal &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Australia_policy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;White Australia Policy&lt;/a&gt; has a lot to reconcile with, especially as we have grown into a truly ethnically diverse nation. The history, the topics, the stories and perspectives shared in the series really were amazingly compelling. It took me a while to get through the series, I&#39;ve had to stop and think at certain points along the way to really unpack what was just introduced. The latest of these was when the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markedness&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Markedness&lt;/a&gt; was introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>June 2024</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/07-07-june-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-07-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/07-07-june-2024/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The Vibe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well winter certainly descended this year. I felt it more than usual having switched to walking the dog in the mornings. The 6:20am wake up was now in complete darkness and so got to witness a few sunrises. We’ve had a few cold days - no frosts, but the days where it’s windy are icy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather has challenged my whole exercise regime. I’ve kept up my long walks with Frankie on the weekend, but I have not visited the gym that often. I find the short days of winter take it out of me. It’s hard to be motivated and stay motivated. There are quite a lot of personal projects that have not received the time they deserve, and part of that is just feeling mentally spent at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason for that is the merger. I’m now fully involved in merger work and being challenged by how things are being done. There’s a lot of rhetoric about codesign and collaboration, but they are just words on a page. There’s very little productive collaboration or engagement baked into any of the processes, and we are defaulting back to the good old hierarchy. And I’m so far down the ranks that it’s impossible to influence decision-making, flag risks, or contribute to anything meaningful. Despite 5 years of experience doing this exact thing, I, and most of my colleagues, have been siloed and ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the talk about well-being and being people-centred flies out the window in this situation. I keep trying to limit my personal investment in this thing - it is just a job, but it’s so hard to do that from a professional integrity perspective. I don’t let projects fail, I don’t let mediocre work continue, I don’t keep making the same mistakes. But that’s also when I can influence the process and what’s happening. I don’t have that now, so it’s just one frustration after another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the professional face goes on at work, but there are cracks. I know I come off sometimes as a critic, but offering &lt;em&gt;critique&lt;/em&gt; is not the same. It’s just that managerialism brings a complete lack of practicality or awareness of the work required. Knowing the jobs to be done is not the same as &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the job is done, which becomes more obvious daily. There’s a massive disconnect between the numbers on the spreadsheet and how to achieve the expected outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My beef comes from our current work that requires 1800 courses to be developed in 18 months, all produced in 10-week cycles. This is the first project I’ve ever worked on where no one can or will tell me, “What is a course? What are the expectations of what will be in a course within this time frame? What is the deliverable? What does ‘done’ look like?”. I have led projects, managed them, planned, developed, cost and implemented them from inception to completion - this is the first time I don’t know what we’re doing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, life outside of work has been good. My Aunt and Uncle visited. However, Frankie was not a fan of a new male in the house and made my Uncle feel quite intimidated. He is such a different dog around others, especially men in our home. I know it’s the protecting nature of the pack, but we will need to do some training on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one of the weekends, we headed out to K1 winery and did a tasting in their very pretty cellar door, looking across the pond and the trees still in their autumn hues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did manage to do one creative thing — building &lt;a href=&quot;https://alt-adl.fun/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Alt Adelaide&lt;/a&gt; as a parody to the branding due to be unveiled on the 15th of July.  Curious how it pans out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Watched&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt21072112/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Bodkin&lt;/a&gt; - watched with the family, a dark humoured murder mystery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://m.imdb.com/title/tt16418808/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Sugar&lt;/a&gt; - interesting film noir style detective show with a bit of a twist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Listened&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been listening to a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://sceneonradio.org/seeing-white/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Scene on Radio&lt;/a&gt; over the last few months, but I got stuck on the Seeing Whiteness series.  I stopped not because of the quality, but because of an idea from Chenjerai Kumanyika - who spoke of &lt;strong&gt;Race as a Technology&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chenjerai Kumanyika&lt;/strong&gt;: Yeah but I have to be honest. I&#39;m proud of Blackness but I&#39;ve come to see it less as my, you know, an identity, and more as, like, a technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Biewen&lt;/strong&gt;: Meaning?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chenjerai Kumanyika&lt;/strong&gt;: Yeah, it’s kind of a weird word, but I see it as a technology because I see Blackness as not something that is hardwired into our biology, that just determines who we are. Instead it’s something that we use. And I have to think about it like that because I have to recognise the way that it can also be used against us. And when it&#39;s being used against us, I cast a sceptical and pessimistic eye toward it. Right? But, you know, I&#39;m trying to be sensitive to, like, where Blackness, where the technology of Blackness fails. You use that technology, and it doesn&#39;t tell you what you need to know about a group of people or a person. But also to navigate in this white supremacist country and to live with a sense of political clarity and joy and possibility, I also tap into that other side of Blackness I was talking about earlier. And I&#39;m optimistic about, you know, tapping into those resources&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That stopped in me in my tracks and I needed to stop and think through that. I still want to unpack the idea more, but I&#39;ve started listening again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The State of the Merger</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/06-28-the-state-of-the-merger/"/>
    <updated>2024-06-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/06-28-the-state-of-the-merger/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post a few months ago when merger work was well underway. I didn&#39;t post it then, hoping things would change. But to honest they haven&#39;t. While progress has been made, each step along the way follows a script that&#39;s pretty similar to what&#39;s below, regardless of the size and scale of the individual piece of work. If I were to describe my view of &lt;a href=&quot;https://adelaideuni.edu.au/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;the current state of the merger&lt;/a&gt;, it would be this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you’re an architect. You meet a client. They have secured financing, the buy-in of some pretty influential backers, and a mandate to build one of the greatest buildings in the world and put Adelaide on the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an architect, this sounds great. It&#39;s a dream job, a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity. So you sit down with the client to start forming a brief, but they’re distracted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s so much to do. We need to start marketing this thing, get the plans in, and get ready for tenants now!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you say sounds great, but let’s start with some fundamentals - what kind of building do you want this to be?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The greatest. World class. We are going to be a magnet for overseas investment and visitors while providing a key service to the state.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That’s fantastic, so what is this building going to DO that allows that to occur?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, it needs to be flexible. We want the highest possible quality experience for everyone who visits. And for those who can’t make it, the same quality experience online! Yes! We have to have the greatest experience for everyone. This is going to make us world-class.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wow, that sounds amazing, but WHAT is IT? Tell me, what is the core experience you want to deliver?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, we need it to be modular so that people can customise their experience. We need flexibility so they can come to us from anywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OK. So I think we still need to understand what are they coming FOR?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Look, we want to be a people-first organisation, and we want to reflect the diversity of our people, their culture, and that of the First Nations. We have to be accessible and ensure we have people’s well-being at the forefront.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That sounds really worthwhile. But we want to get into some details now. In order for us to draw up any plans, we want to make sure we understand the function of the space. To ensure that we can build the best buildings, we find that knowing what you want them to be there for and what you want them to do while they are in the building is important. Mistakes made in planning can be really expensive later on. It’s best for us to get as full a picture of what you need, and we can do the design work and sort out the details.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, that’s great. We need to get the plans off to the council in 15 days. We’ve set up meetings next week with our staff, and they will tell you what materials to use and the dimensions they come in. Ok, well, that was a great meeting. I have to rush! Have a branding meeting for the new logo. Bye!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They leave, and the door shuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your phone buzzes continually for a minute as 25 notifications inform you of meetings you’re now attending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>May 2024</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/06-03-may-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/06-03-may-2024/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The Vibe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The month of May was when everything went off the rails. I came back from my travels, got sick and needed a couple of weeks to recover from that. It wasn&#39;t COVID, it wasn&#39;t the flu, but it definitely knocked me on my arse and I needed quite a bit of recuperation. The disruption to my routine really resonated throughout the month, and it just felt like everything struggled to get back on track after that. The last week, everything kicked back in, but man it took a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the vibe? Well I feel a bit lost. I need some time to get my head back in the game, but that&#39;s challenged by finding the time and space to do so. I need to get things back on track in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work-wise, we were in full steam in terms of merger work, which was good and bad. I really don&#39;t feel that the process was as productive as it could have been. But at the same time, I quite enjoyed facilitating the workshop and getting back to working more closely with academic staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Aurora, or out attempt to go and see the aurora. Ms A and I packed the car with Frankie and hit the road to head south to where the best viewing was expected. As we drove away from home and the city we could easily see the pink glow through the windscreen. It was great! But we kept heading south... and then nothing. The aurora died down, and the clouds came in! It was a bit of fun, and we did see pink! No photos despite packing the camera and tripod. The next night we headed down to Moana beach and enjoyed walking the dog at sunset with the aim of hanging out till dark in the hope of another aurora showing. While there were no lights, the sunset was off the charts! Such amazing light - the moon was out, it was amazing! (see photos)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Watched&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.imdb.com/title/tt12037194/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Furiosa&lt;/a&gt; at a special screening put on by Krix Speakers where they had done a reference setup of the movie at the Wallis Cinema in Noarlunga. The movie itself was just OK - it was not anywhere near as good as Fury Road - but the sound! It was amazing. The seperation was amazing - nothing was muffled and the way that the V8 engines blended and became musical in the soundtrack was beautiful. There was also a lot of leather in the movie - so lots of squeaking I&#39;m not sure I would have heard before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.imdb.com/title/tt12637874/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Fallout&lt;/a&gt; and loved the 50&#39;s aesthetic and quirky humour of the series. I&#39;ve never played the game, but I got sucked into the world very quickly. I do love the ethical and moral quandaries it deals with and the depth that it goes into. There&#39;s a lot to the series - and so I might need to pick up the controller for a play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms A and I watched both Dune movies together. I needed a bit of a reminder of the first movie before sitting down with the second. I was surprised with Ms A&#39;s attention span lasting for both movies (watched over a couple of weekend, not back to back). They are visually stunning movies and I loved the lore and soundtrack too. I would love a Krix cinema experience of it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Listened&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Season 3 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://longlead.com/article/long-shadow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Long Shadow&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;In Guns Guns We Trust&lt;/em&gt; was phenomenal. I would recommend this to anyone who wants to understand guns in America. At the end of the day it&#39;s still a mystery that nothing has changed despite the carnage, but it was interesting to chart the history and learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great series was the ABC&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/listen/programs/expanse/roddans-diamonds/101358708&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Expanse&lt;/a&gt;. All three seasons are great, tackling the Argyle Diamond Heist, the sinking of the Blythe Star and the Pine Gap spy base. Each one is told by a different reporter and has it&#39;s own vibe and production, but each story is compelling and riveting. Perfect to binge on.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>April 2024</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/05-12-april-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-05-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/05-12-april-2024/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h3&gt;The Vibe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April has felt like a big month. There was quite a bit of travel, social events, and family time packed in, which led to feeling quite disjointed and out of routine. Most weeks weren&#39;t full work weeks – they were broken up with public holidays and leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel bad about addressing most of my health goals and letting a lot of the big effort items fall to the wayside, and I have felt guilty about it. I also feel very tired, with the first 1/3rd of the year being full-on and a lot has been happening. That&#39;s led to a loss of routine and a real inability to stay focused and get things done. I&#39;ve got to put some time aside this next week to bring things back into focus and set my attention back on what matters. I can see that my default state is to drop back into being reactive, leading me to not make decisions, not communicate properly, and feeling scatter-brained in almost every aspect of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was due to do an audit of my Focus Course progress this month - I haven&#39;t done it, but I realise that I actually need to set aside some time to get it done. That said I feel a good chunk of the big picture items - my vision and values in particular - has really helped steer the ship and stay on course throughout the chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing I wanted to note - this was an unlucky month. On my trip to Wollongong I left cables and my kindle at a friends place, lost my glasses for the first time in my life (20+ years of wearing glasses!). I also had a trip to the emergency department for a minor issue. I&#39;ve come away wondering what&#39;s going on or if it&#39;s just my time for a streak of bad luck. Hopefully this is all for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The month kicked off with the Easter weekend which was some great family and social time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next week saw the start of the school holidays and the family headed over to Tasmania for 5 days. Some dear friends move over there a few years ago and we haven&#39;t seen them for a couple of years, so when flights were on sale during the school holidays I jumped on them and booked us in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasmania is the smallest state in Australia, an island off the island (or mainland, a word you only use in Tassie!). It&#39;s been 14 years since Mrs K and I had been there last, one of our first &amp;quot;grown-up&amp;quot; holidays. I thought that Tassie had been through a boom since then, you here a lot more about in the news as it&#39;s become popular with retirees, but the reality is that the state&#39;s population is still very small, just &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tasmania&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;571,165 people&lt;/a&gt;.  Driving through Hobart I was expecting it to be bigger, but it&#39;s just a dot in terms of a city with a bit of sprawl up the river Derwent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up the river we went to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Museum_of_Old_and_New_Art&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;MONA&lt;/a&gt; – the Museum of Old and New Art. The largest private gallery in the Southern Hemisphere MONA is a statement. I&#39;m not 100% sure what it says, given the owner David Walsh made his money as a professional gambler, but the museum seems to be hewn out of the rock and contains a broad and eclectic collection of art and artefacts. There are strong themes of sex and death throughout - and in some cases it comes across as a bit try-hard and teenage-angsty. But at the same time there is a uniqueness to the works and the experience over all. There were a couple of works that I really enjoyed – the Fat Porsche being one - but MONA is more about the experience, and some of the pieces just need to seen, heard and smelt. Speaking of the experience - I feel really sorry for the army of teenagers and 20 somethings required to be employed simply to tell older visitors not to touch the artworks. Having spent a large amount of time being around toddlers in my life, these Boomers were incredibly disrespectful and annoying, wanting to poke and prod the artworks in every space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then drove our hired Tesla Model Y (which I will review) through the gorgeous countryside to Launceston. We met up with our friends in their new home perched high on the hill above town and were back in the groove quickly. Our girls had been together and best friends in daycare, and they just slotted back into their ways within minutes. It was great to see their friendship, which had been pretty distant, spark up again so quickly. They were inseparable for the rest of the time we spent there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next few days, we descended into the rainforest, completed a maize maze, went to the beach, wandered the city, saw some monkeys, visited a winery, drank a lot of Pinot Noir, climbed a mountain, and genuinely connected with our people and the country. For the last evening, we drove back to Hobart to spend time with our extended family there and got to enjoy the views from their amazing house and the experience of the most sincere hospitality on the planet! There was also an afternoon of whiskey cocktails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After arriving home we quickly washed Ms A&#39;s clothes and the next day she flew up to Sydney to spend some time with her Aunty, Uncle and cousins. I went back to work and ran some workshops to aid the design of courses for the new university as part of the merger work, which was ... interesting. It wasn&#39;t organised well, so there was a lot of on the fly problem solving - but we were working with a great group of people throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a nice, quiet adult weekend where we probably tried to recover from a very hectic week before I flew off to Wollongong for my uncle&#39;s 70th birthday. It was a bit of a family do, and it was great to see my mum, brother, sis-in-law, niece, aunt, uncles and cousins growing family. We had a great long lunch with amazing Italian food and carried on at my other uncle&#39;s local haunts. I had some time to catch up with a prior colleague, Lindy, and catch up about life, the universe, and everything over a meal and a bottle of wine. I also got to see Kate, catch up on the family goings, and discuss the state of higher education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite action-packed and some great photos to boot!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/48074786@N06&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53668429641_0228e1443d_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Watched&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s Super Rugby season, so a lot of Rugby! Watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1136617/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The Killer&lt;/a&gt; - which wasn&#39;t great, and binged through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2934286/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Halo&lt;/a&gt; - again not great but held my attention for 2 seasons (but I am a sucker for Sci Fi).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Listened&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#39;t recommend enough &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoutlawocean.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The Outlaw Ocean&lt;/a&gt;. This superbly reported and told a set of stories gave me a real insight into a world I knew very little about - what actually goes on out at sea.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>March 2024</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/04-01-march-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-04-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/04-01-march-2024/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h3&gt;The Vibe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March this year was a lot of fun from the family and social aspects. We spent a lot of time together as a family, getting out and doing stuff together. Ms A. has settled into high school life and has started making new social connections and so we have had a bunch of visitors to the home. This has led us to the discovery that Frankie has a &amp;quot;self-defence&amp;quot; mechanism where he excretes a god-awful rotting fish smell when strange men (dads sent in to pick up their daughters) come into the house! He&#39;s all bark and no bite, but the smell is savage!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started on our V2 of kitchen renovations, so I&#39;ve been busy pulling together our ideas into a format for the joiner to draw up some plans and give us a quote. That&#39;s taken up a large part of my creative energy for the last couple of weeks. I&#39;m really happy with the result - maybe less so with the cost, so I&#39;m hoping we can make a couple of changes to reduce some aspects, and now it&#39;s off to the bank to see about a loan. We&#39;ve been lucky, given the rising house prices, that despite not doing anything to improve the value apart from sitting on it, the local neighbourhood has risen quite a lot, so it shouldn&#39;t be an issue for the bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/images/New-Design.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen Design&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the career front, I&#39;m not feeling that great. The Job is a struggle. I love my team and my peers, but there is a constant background from leadership ... not leading. If you&#39;re going to lead, you have to act and do things that empower your people - at the moment, it is the complete opposite of that. And if there is an opportunity for the operations team to move and get things done, it gets shut down. So rather than moving forward, we are spending extreme amounts of energy and capacity moving backwards — because despite the team&#39;s need to move forward, we are being dragged back into the old default ways of working — hierarchy, power dynamics, information asymmetry, whispers and favourites. I don&#39;t know if I feel this more than others because I&#39;m more aware of the issues, but I can&#39;t seem to move the needle on this. I have tried to communicate the issues and offer a ton of solutions, and yet there is zero engagement, let alone any acknowledgment. The culture is becoming more and more toxic around me, and while there is a desire just to put my head down and stay out of it, it&#39;s impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has led to me having less energy to devote to my career other objectives. The job is just one part of all of this, my aim is to build up more aspects of my career beyond the job. And that&#39;s happening! I had a couple of real bright spots this month with a couple of people reaching out over LinkedIn to discuss my work and some web stats pointing to some intriguing engagements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had two fantastic conversations with learning design colleagues about the work I&#39;ve been doing around Learning Design Systems. They were great conversations and made me and the work I&#39;ve been doing feel valued (sometimes more so than The Job!).  I loved the fact that both conversations came from people stumbling across my work, finding &lt;a href=&quot;https://timklapdor.wordpress.com/2022/10/27/a-learning-design-system/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mediaproduction.adelaide.edu.au/online-design-system/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;websites&lt;/a&gt; that I&#39;ve worked on but never fully &amp;quot;finished&amp;quot;. It annoyed me as I did submit a paper to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ascilite.org/annual-conference/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Ascilite&lt;/a&gt; last year, which Reviewer 2 didn&#39;t like, and so it didn&#39;t go through, and while I understand the system, it was disappointing. I didn&#39;t have the energy to push back on the decision or really look at resubmitting elsewhere, but I probably should have because it was an attempt to document the system as a whole. I think I might stick it &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/developing-a-learning-design-system/&quot;&gt;up on here on the blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other interesting find was the use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://learning-patterns.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Learning Patterns&lt;/a&gt;. I turned on some basic web analytics to get a sense of engagement and saw a spike in visitors from Spain. Hmmmm, I wonder why? Looking through some of the logs I found this resource &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://view.genial.ly/65ce25578c35460014799729/interactive-content-retos-de-la-educacion-medica-planeacion&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Challenges of medical education. Importance of planning&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. I don&#39;t speak any Spanish, but I love the fact that this exists and that the video demonstrates how easy it has become to translate something on the web these days — a click of a button in the browser and all of a sudden, my English site becomes natively Spanish! I hope they say good things in the video - but to be honest, I love the fact that this exists!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from a bigger perspective, the career progresses well even if The Job is spluttering along!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healthwise - things are OK. I&#39;m doing well on the walking and general activity. My Apple Watch informed me I was averaging 10km a day - so that&#39;s good. I need to work on getting to the gym more - adding an extra session or two would be great, but have found the balancing act of schedules hard to manage. Eating is OK too, but could certainly be better - this last week wasn&#39;t great with socialising, being out and Easter all happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went and saw Mr Bungle with Dave and Stu. It wasn&#39;t what I expected or anticipated - being basically a thrash metal gig rather than anything close to any from California. It had its merits, and it was good to see members of Slayer and Anthrax, as well as Mike Paton, strutting around the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms A and I also went to Womad on the Sunday. It was a stinking hot day, getting up into the 40s and so the struggle with the heat was very real. We saw Wildfire Manwurrk, Connie Bailey Rae, Witch, Dubioza Kolektiv (probably the first band that kicked it the day off as the sun was going down and they had a great selection of ska/gypsy/reggae and rap. Was great fun!)., Ibibo Sound Machine (great club funk sound) and Moonlight Benjamin - who were my pick of the day. We watched the whole set and it was mind-blowing! Described as a &amp;quot;voodoo queen priestess&amp;quot; Benjamin was truly amazing and captivating. I swear she was casting spells on stage and had the audience captivated. She had the perfect frontman persona, strutting on stage and working the audience. The rest of the band was great with a fantastic Vox driven raw and heavy blues rock sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clare and I celebrated our anniversary of being together - 24 years! Had a great meal out at Bandit in Unley and did the Feed Me Menu there (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mastodon.social/@timklapdor/112121320240195957&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;not this one&lt;/a&gt;!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; data-footer=&quot;true&quot; data-context=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/timklapdor/53624342329/in/album-72177720314386151/&quot; title=&quot;Morning colours&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53624342329_13112a7466_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;Morning colours&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Watched&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got through a few different shows - but would recommend the following documentaries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love Has Won&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telemarketers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Listened&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m still listening to a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fourstrokebaron.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Four Stroke Baron&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big month of podcasts this month and quite a few I would recommend:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Behind the Bastards series on &lt;a href=&quot;https://omny.fm/shows/behind-the-bastards/part-one-the-terrible-secret-of-steve-jobs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The Terrible Secret of Steve Jobs&lt;/a&gt; is really well done and quite horrific. I have a real issue with hero worship and this is basically why - despite success in many areas, a lot of people are horrible in others. Their work isn&#39;t a reflection of their behaviour in other areas of their life. While Jobs can be lauded for his ability to shape the tech world he was also a stinky goblin and deadbeat and abusive Dad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/m001w206&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The Gatekeepers&lt;/a&gt; is a really useful series on the history of social media and the discussion of them as gatekeepers. The series threads the historical perspectives of silicon valley and the narrative it has constructed for itself (challenging the powers that be while being very much of and for those same powers) and contrasts that with their &lt;em&gt;actual effects&lt;/em&gt; on societies. The Rest Of World episode is really important in this story but it is hard to go past the emotional trauma of The Vortex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I smashed through Season 2 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://pod.link/1592984136&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Things Fell Apart&lt;/a&gt; over a couple of days. I am a huge fan of Jon Ronson, and I love his foray into these butterfly effect stories that seek to trace back the origins of ripples we feel today. Highly recommend the series and I think I will need to listen again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ed Zitron has been doing the rounds in my feed this month. He was on the Steve Jobs series on BTB, also made an appearance on Tech Won&#39;t Save Us and has launched his own podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://omny.fm/shows/better-offline?cloudflare-language=en-US&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Better Offline&lt;/a&gt;. My pick of the early episodes is &lt;a href=&quot;https://overcast.fm/+BGz69GfLgE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The Rot Economy&lt;/a&gt;. The episode seems to be an attempt to mix a conversation and Ed&#39;s more scripted elements and doesn&#39;t quite work in that seamless flow - which might just be a teething problem in an early episode, but the topic is spot on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Read&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rot Economy episode of Ed Zitron&#39;s podcast led me to one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ez.substack.com/p/the-rot-economy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Ed&#39;s blog posts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public and private investors, along with the markets themselves, have become entirely decoupled from the concept of what “good” business truly is, focusing on one metric — one &lt;em&gt;truly noxious&lt;/em&gt; metric — over all else: growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Growth” in this case is not necessarily about being “bigger” or “better,” it is simply “more.” It means that the company is generating more revenue, higher valuations, gaining more market share, and then finding more ways to generate these things. Businesses are expected to be - and rewarded for being - eternal burning engines of capital that create more and more shareholder value while, hopefully, providing a service to a customer in the process. In the public markets, that means that &lt;a href=&quot;https://ez.substack.com/p/techs-elite-hates-labor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;companies like Google, Meta, and Microsoft&lt;/a&gt; were rewarded for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/9daf27f6-dde7-40d8-b01d-33b70844aa69&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;having unfocused, capital-intensive businesses that required mass layoffs when times got tough&lt;/a&gt;, because the market loved the idea that they’d found a way to save money. They weren’t punished for their poor planning, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/thomas-koulopoulos/why-this-13-year-google-employee-says-google-can-no-longer-innovate.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;their stagnating products&lt;/a&gt;, their mismanagement of human capital, or their general lack of any real innovation because &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the numbers kept going up.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This analysis is pretty spot on and can be evidenced in a number of ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zuckerberg burnt through $10billion, didn&#39;t produce a product and remains in charge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The massive variations in HR over the last few years where we see swings of up to 20% of their workforce being hired or fired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The on going degradation of services and products to the point we now have a new term — &amp;quot;enshitification&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lack of any real and meaningful innovation from Silicon Valley for the past decade.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lack of real products from Silicon Valley - we&#39;ve actually gone beyond needing customers or delivering services - it&#39;s literally just the Ponzi scheme now - see Crypto!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Job vs Career</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-11-job-vs-career/"/>
    <updated>2024-03-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-11-job-vs-career/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started 2024 with a bit of time off to spend contemplating my current state, assessing it and starting to plan out the future. One of the big issues and points of conflict and dissatisfaction during 2023 was my job. I had to really dig into this idea and came to the realisation that it was my job that was making me unhappy — not my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That distinction — Job vs Career — wasn’t apparent before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Job had become all-consuming and demanding. Having some space and time away from it gave me a better perspective, especially since the two aren’t the same. They’re not even interchangeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A career contains a multitude of jobs. Some of them are the ones you get paid for, but many of them aren’t. And that’s often where the confusion comes into play. The paid job begins to bleed into other areas, and you associate the paid job with all the other jobs. They get lumped together as a career, but they are distinct and need to be kept separate. It’s our mind that blends them together, so every so often, we need to pull focus, reevaluate and paint in the edges to make it clear what our jobs really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the selling points of the Focus Course is &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt;, both to see things more closely and direct our attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reflection, I can say that for the last few years, I’ve paid too much attention to my paid job and not my career. I’ve allowed the job to expand beyond its parameters and edges to consume everything around it—my time, attention, and priorities. What I need to do, and what I plan to do in 2024, is to switch that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to focus on my &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;career&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, not my &lt;em&gt;job&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say I won’t be working or pulling my weight; what I’m saying is that my focus will be my &lt;strong&gt;career&lt;/strong&gt; and the multiple other jobs that make &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; up. The other jobs to be done are learning, writing, sharing, connecting, communicating, and organising - all the things that I need and want in my career that my job can’t provide.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>February 2024</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-04-february-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-03-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-04-february-2024/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h3&gt;The Vibe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So 2024 and a &#39;long&#39; February. I could feel the weight of that extra day 😁!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February kicked off with a return to work and the start of high school for my daughter. Ms A has adapted quickly to high school life, I wish I could say the same about work. It came as a bit of a shock, but one of the great things was that despite a couple of issues coming up while I was away, my team stepped in and solved them while I was away! So my inbox was reading through a bunch of email threads that began &amp;quot;Thanks for all your work on getting that resolved.&amp;quot; and me going back through the chain to find out WTF had happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the weekly routine has been a challenge. I got very used to having lots of time to exercise and ponder the world around me. Exercising has mostly consisted of walking the dog in the morning daily, a weekday gym visit, maybe one on the weekend, and an extended hike on Saturday morning. This has aligned with my aims of exercising and getting out into nature - so I&#39;m really happy with how things have gone in that space. I&#39;d like to make more room for the gym, but getting to and from the office, cooking, and chores means there&#39;s not a lot of time and energy left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been commuting into the city on the train daily. This has been great as I&#39;m able to write on the way to work and do this every day. I think February has been my most prolific on the blog for ages, and I feel really good about it. I haven&#39;t got around to writing much about learning design, which is one of my goals, but every Saturday during my hike, I&#39;ve been taking voice notes and have been pulling a lot of scattered ideas together. Given that &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/i-don&#39;t-think-in-words/&quot;&gt;I don&#39;t think in words&lt;/a&gt; this to me is progress. The words are coming; they&#39;re just not all there yet or as coherent as I&#39;d like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been making roads towards my side hustle. I&#39;ve got a logo, domain and email setup – just need some content now! (If you read this and are curious - DM me, and we can chat).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was some shocking news from a colleague who had only recently left the team that their partner had died suddenly. It was a massive shock to myself and the team. I am flummoxed on what to do in the face of other people&#39;s grief as I know how private and personal that process is and needs to be. We can always share the loss, but not the grief - that&#39;s up to us to process, and we all do it differently. I gave to the GoFundMe that popped up as being interstate made it impossible to really do or contribute anything. I&#39;m deeply shocked and emotional about the family and the loss. Anyone losing a parent is a callback to my own experience of losing my dad and the ongoing pangs of grief and sadness that come with it. That mortal coil is a thing and we the fact we are here is always precarious, but damn we get our hooks into those around us and we get ripped apart when they go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished the Focus Course, and you can read up on my notes and progress. I&#39;d happily recommend doing the course and have used a lot of the concepts back at work and I feel much more confident about life the universe and everything. And that&#39;s honestly where my vibe is at. Things are moving, and they are good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s officially &lt;strong&gt;Mad March&lt;/strong&gt; here in Adelaide - where we cram in every possible cultural event into the last two weeks of February and three of March. The Fringe is on and I&#39;ve been to a couple of shows already. I&#39;ve got my ticket to WOMAD - just a day of the festival this year&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/48074786@N06&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53564483153_2ae83ae7f8_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Recommended&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Watch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Criminal Record on AppleTV - I enjoyed this series. Loved the play on sympathy and good vs. bad that was covered in the show. Great performances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Super Rugby - It&#39;s back! This is going to be the year of rebuilding Australian Rugby and this is where it all needs to start. There&#39;s already been turmoil with clubs on the verge of going bust and a threat to whole competition, but at the same time the game remains the same. Some great matchups coming and looking forward to what comes from this season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Listened&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chameleon S07 The Michigan Plot - This is another one that questions the tactics of the FBI, but a bit more of a tangled mess. Dealing with a militia plot to kidnap a sitting governor, it&#39;s a captivating story full of bumbling fools, untouched bravado, bullshit and horrific casual threats of violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dark Net Diaries - Another great episode on &lt;a href=&quot;https://darknetdiaries.com/episode/92/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The Pirate Bay&lt;/a&gt;. I loved the more philosophical elements of the discussion in the episode. I have always liked Peter Sunde and his coverage in the media. The way he tried to challenge the status quo was admirable, and I loved the discussion of the law in Sweden and the huge differences between it and the US legal system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Read&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wheresyoured.at/sam-altman-fried/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Subprime Intelligence&lt;/a&gt; - Loved this piece from Ed Zitron. I cleared out a couple of posts from my drafts on AI this week as they&#39;d been bugging me. As soon as I hit publish then along comes Ed with this knock out piece. So many links and research - this is exactly what&#39;s needed around AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jenniferplusplus.com/losing-the-imitation-game/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Losing the imitation game&lt;/a&gt; - Another AI post, this time from Jennifer Moore. This is a great explainer about the hype and technical operations of AI that seems to get lost in the noise.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Understanding and Meaning</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-02-understanding-and-meaning/"/>
    <updated>2024-03-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-02-understanding-and-meaning/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;So my &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; got &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.downes.ca/cgi-bin/page.cgi?post=76311&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Downes&#39;d&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, which is nice, but at the same time, Stephen&#39;s commentary can be challenging. In his brief commentary, he laid out his issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, sounds great, until you push a bit on what counts exactly as &#39;understanding&#39; and &#39;meaning&#39;. What is &#39;understanding&#39;? Knowledge of causal principles? Not robust enough. General laws and principles? Too inflexible. A model or world view? Sure, now we&#39;re getting closer. But that&#39;s what AIs do! Kids learning &#39;why&#39; - what sort of answer do you give them? Cause, principles, theory. Right? So what is there to &#39;understanding&#39; that AIs don&#39;t do. The same sort of questions arise around &#39;meaning&#39;. Do we mean &#39;intentionality&#39;? &#39;Intensionality?&#39; &amp;quot;emotions or tone&amp;quot; Aw, we &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; know AI can respond to these. It&#39;s too easy to simply say &amp;quot;understanding &amp;amp; meaning.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let me expand a little more, as I think it&#39;s useful to delve a little deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen provides a couple of options for framing understanding, but I&#39;d like to keep it simple. Understanding is not just the knowledge of a thing; you must also grasp its cause or explanation. It is a deeper sense of what the thing is, but also how it has come to be. It isn&#39;t just knowing the definition of the words but the context in which you would use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s apply that definition: The thing in the example of ChatGPT is text. Yes, it knows that object quite well and intimately. But it doesn&#39;t grasp cause or explanation. As I said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT didn&#39;t learn the topic, it did no research, it did no validation, and it contributed no novel thoughts, ideas or concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it can demonstrate &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; of a specific domain. A &lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt; of that knowledge, yes. However, a model is not the same as understanding. The &#39;worldview&#39; this AI has isn&#39;t worldly, connected or contextual - it is within a specific domain. There is no connection to other models or concepts or bodies of knowledge or to the world it inhabits. Those are the elements that generate understanding. These particular models are purely mathematical - they are calculations of the most &lt;em&gt;probable&lt;/em&gt; correct answer. This is what Large Language Models do - calculate. They don&#39;t do anything else to achieve their end results - which can be impressive and look like intelligence created them - but that&#39;s not how they were achieved. The LLM never understood your request, it just performed a series of complex pattern matching and weighted the results to what calculated to the most correct answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding on the other hand, based on the definition about, would include triangulating that answer more broadly and across a broader area of knowledge, experience, connections, and contexts. It would also include coming back without an answer - or with additional questions and clarifications. Or not providing an answer if the context and what was asked was wrong or inappropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI, as it stands, has none of those features so it cannot understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to meaning, Stephen offers a couple more suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we mean &#39;intentionality&#39;? &#39;Intensionality?&#39; &amp;quot;emotions or tone&amp;quot;[?]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, meaning has more to do with seeking an answer, asking why, and seeking to find out about the cause and effect and reason for things to occur. In that sense, it is about intentionality and less about the others. Seeking out and finding meaning is beyond an algorithms capability because it is not sentient, alive or intelligence. Stephen&#39;s next line illustrates that perfectly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aw, we &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; know AI can respond to these&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respond&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; — exactly. It doesn&#39;t engage in making meaning, it can&#39;t because its just calculations, and even they have to be kicked off by an executable command.  There&#39;s also oodles of examples that show how badly generative tools can respond. They don&#39;t understand the meaning of math, humour, sarcasm, fingers, nuance or language as a vessel for emotion. But we can and do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There isn&#39;t a single step in the algorithm that involves making meaning from what it outputs. It is pattern matching. It&#39;s good at that yes, but that is not making meaning. Readable, legible, spelling and grammar - they are patterns. Meaning is not. AI is just code — anything beyond that, and it is us creating (or buying in) the illusion. These are the parlour tricks I&#39;ve mentioned - it &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; intelligent, and if we &lt;em&gt;speak&lt;/em&gt; of it as intelligence, we lend credence to it being &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; of as intelligence. But it isn&#39;t. &lt;a href=&quot;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbots-emily-m-bender.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;It&#39;s just code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now look, I&#39;ll be honest - I&#39;m getting outside my comfort zone here. I don&#39;t have the background to jump into a philosophical debate around the different interpretations of meaning and understanding, as they seem like contested concepts across multiple disciplines. What I contend is that regardless of that nuance — what is being done by generative AI is not an example of intelligence. That all of the generative tools out there today do not represent anything intelligent. They don&#39;t function like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a huge amount of confusion about what &amp;quot;AI&amp;quot; does, how it does it, and what it &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; to do. There is a mislabelling (which is intentional) to rebrand machine learning and other big data concepts as &amp;quot;intelligence&amp;quot;. By labelling this technology intelligence, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;we&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; perform the gestalt and apply the concepts that sit alongside it. We apply traits and behaviours that don&#39;t actually exist. By doing so we become part of the hallucination of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doug Belshaw &lt;a href=&quot;https://thoughtshrapnel.com/2024/03/02/language-is-probably.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;linked out &lt;/a&gt;to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jenniferplusplus.com/losing-the-imitation-game/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;a great post by Jennifer Moore&lt;/a&gt; who makes this argument much better than I. She goes into the operations of AI, how an LLM works. I&#39;d already picked this up from my own research and experience, but I don&#39;t think I could have explained it as simply as she does.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Terms of Service</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-02-terms-of-service/"/>
    <updated>2024-03-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/03-02-terms-of-service/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m being spammed by a bunch of companies that are updating their &lt;strong&gt;Terms of Service&lt;/strong&gt;. These long legal documents have become the default for every web service as a self-made get-out-of-jail-free card. They tend to outline how they aren’t liable for any loss you would encounter, they’re not responsible for maintaining their services and your data, and any loss or damage you may encounter using THEIR service is YOUR problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are written in legalese, an impenetrable dialect of English full of loopholes, double meaning and antiquated terminology that only a minority of the population can decipher, usually only to the extent that an entirely contradictory point of view can be extracted from the same text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s also the presentation. These aren’t meant to be read. They’re usually hidden from view rather than presented to the user. They have no readability or accessibility features and usually lack basic formatting or stylistic elements like headings, indentation, etc. There’s also the microscopic font size and language used. Legalese obviously had no copy editors or understanding of their audience to present them with valid and useful information. There is only the kitchen sink - which will be hurled at you if anything goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m curious… how valid are these as legal documents?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean seriously, in an objective verdict-by-your-peers way. If you presented a terms of service document to a jury, would it be seen as valid? Yes, the words exonerate the companies, but don’t they have a duty of care? If they take your money, that is also contractual. So, can you sell a service and then deny or not deliver it because of a loophole you created?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing I&#39;m interested in is the process of gaining agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But you signed it…” but did I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’ve ever “signed” anything online. Despite the technical geniuses in Silicon Valley, I have yet to encounter any technology capable of capturing my signature - the physical act of me signing my name as authorisation and acceptance. Most lack anything like a pen to complete the task or the resolution that would allow anyone to meaningfully verify and compare signatures. Is clicking a button or ticking a box an adequate equivalent? No physicality, no unique identifier, no sense of authorisation. If a bot can do it, then it’s not really a signature, nor should it qualify as an equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d also question the timing of the “acceptance”. Most services require you to accept the TOS &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; you can even use the service. How can you make an informed decision without even having a chance to see the service or interact with it? You don’t buy a house, car, or a microwave without the ability to test it out, look around, press some buttons and see if it’s suitable. So, how can an online service justify requiring you to accept a legally binding document BEFORE you use it? How much legal weight are we willing to give the TOS?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a quick FYI that I&#39;ve added my own &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/tos/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Terms of Service&lt;/a&gt; to the site.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intelligence requires understanding &amp; meaning</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;OK, here&#39;s my position: intelligence requires understanding &amp;amp; meaning. Therefore, if you want to call something intelligent, then it must be able to exhibit understanding and meaning. AI, as it stands, can exhibit neither, which leaves it as being &lt;em&gt;Artificial&lt;/em&gt;. Or &lt;em&gt;fake&lt;/em&gt; – which is technically correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am over the promises and hype behind AI. What&#39;s become abundantly clear to me over the last year is that it&#39;s ALL 👏 JUST 👏 HYPE 👏. To go around claiming that ChatGPT is AI is not only misleading, it&#39;s grossly overstating its capabilities. My prediction is that this overhyping will lead to the claims being challenged legally in the next 12 months &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/#fn1&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For something to generate text without an understanding of what those words are or what they mean is not intelligence – it&#39;s a &lt;em&gt;forgery&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT didn&#39;t learn the topic, it did no research, it did no validation, and it contributed no novel thoughts, ideas or concepts. Other people did all of that already. ChatGPT just colonised all of that data - hovering it up without any permission or legal right to do so, just like all the great white guys of the past - and now it can Copy/Paste that information to you in a timely manner because it&#39;s spending $US700k a day on compute. These models don&#39;t know the meaning of the words they generated because they base their sequence on probability, not correctness. The words aren&#39;t checked for correctness or understanding, but comprehension based on similar blocks of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yeah, but it generates new things!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it? On it its own? Does it just come up with entirely new and novel things without, say, a &lt;em&gt;prompt&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. You provided the prompt. You &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;had&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to provide the prompt, or nothing would have happened. You provided the creativity. You did the heavy lifting of thought by generating the prompt. What you outsourced was the labour. You &lt;em&gt;could have&lt;/em&gt; crafted the text yourself, but it would have taken effort. Instead, you outsourced your request to a server farm to process it based on the similarity of the words you were searching for in its colonised and stolen data set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not intelligent; it&#39;s sophisticated — both the mathematics and the hardware on which they&#39;re running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact is that the equation doesn&#39;t seek to understand the text or find meaning in it. For it to work, it doesn&#39;t need to. Instead, it creates shapes and patterns in a mathematically definable format that it can use to compare and predict similarities and fit because, at some point, other people told it what was correct. It&#39;s had years of person-hours telling it where it went wrong and where it was right - we have that too – it&#39;s called childhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, kids learn &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt;. They don&#39;t just learn the patterns of behaviour; they learn the causes and effects. They develop an understanding not just of the shape, but the reason for it. They can understand and create meaning not just from the simple but from the complex. Good parenting, guardianship, and solid relationships do this, and it takes effort and time. It is very different to the behaviourist conditioning of &amp;quot;right&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;wrong&amp;quot; &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/#fn2&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; these models utilise. Children learn across modes, media, instances and locations, social and individual spaces, cultures, and languages. ChatGPT does none of that. It doesn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt;. It cannot relate to emotions or tone; it doesn&#39;t need to make relationships or maintain or grow them. It doesn&#39;t count what it doesn&#39;t need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It simply spits out words. Just words. Like Clippy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above is just about words, but we see the same model being applied to other areas — image generation, voice cloning, videos, search, and soon-to-be every app you touch. They operate in the same mode - adapting pixels and bits based on training data they colonised and stole. And we feed them more data without question. Every app that comes out now is there to hoover up the next data set. Yesterday, they came for your words; now, they come for your prompts. Producing more forgeries along the way, and not just some dodgy text - but fake nudes, political lies, news reports, state propaganda, disinformation &amp;amp; misinformation – stuff that will have a real and tangible impact on the world, on you and your family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t buy into the hype or the &amp;quot;someday-isms&amp;quot;. Look at what&#39;s around today. Ask yourself - will AI do anything to fix this, or will it just make it worse?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will it help you connect with your kid or your partner?&lt;br /&gt;
Will it help with climate change or add to it?&lt;br /&gt;
Will it create more insidious spam?&lt;br /&gt;
Will it just add fuel to the fire?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is — regardless of what we choose, all the worst things &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; happen. Maybe not to us, but every nightmare will happen somewhere in the world because this technology doesn&#39;t understand or mean anything. It doesn&#39;t understand the implications of what it creates. It doesn&#39;t know the meaning of the words or what the pixels in the image mean to someone - it just makes them happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than a superintelligence, we are creating a subprime idiot &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/#fn3&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the first post &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-22-the-hype-machine-is-breaking-us/&quot;&gt;The Hype Machine is Breaking Us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;footnotes-sep&quot; /&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat to AI will be the myriad of legal challenges coming it&#39;s way. Governments are too slow and stupid to react, and markets will have lured in all the suckers and have made off with their billions before anything gets settled. &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Audrey Watters&#39; work on the influence of the behaviourists on technology and Silicon Valley (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/monograph/5138/Teaching-MachinesThe-History-of-Personalized&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Teaching Machines&lt;/a&gt;) is worth tapping into here. &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/#fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;While this was in my drafts, this much richer post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wheresyoured.at/sam-altman-fried/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Subprime Intelligence&lt;/a&gt; from Ed Zitron, was published. I recommend reading it as it contains links and depth that support for the opinion I shared. &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-25-intelligence-requires-understanding-and-meaning/#fnref3&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Hype Machine is Breaking Us</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-22-the-hype-machine-is-breaking-us/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-22-the-hype-machine-is-breaking-us/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;What I’ve noticed with every conversation about AI is the hype. The unbridled enthusiasm, constant media coverage and headline-grabbing are simply unavoidable. It is omnipresent in everything day to day, driving conversations, think pieces, reporting and &#39;thought leadership&#39; to an absolute saturation point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hype points to the undeniable financial underpinnings of this technology more than its actual capabilities. What is the groundbreaking evolution? Where is the evidence that this is revolutionary? All we have are parlour games, smoke, and mirrors. Passable text but never exceptional. Useful but never ready. Brilliant but unstable and untrustworthy. And with an increasing amount of terrible side effects - from more intrusive and &#39;customised&#39; spam through to fake nudes and reality-distorting media, all producible at pennies on the dollar on an unimaginable global scale. To be honest, these aren&#39;t the side effects - this is the product. Fakery on a global scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the coverage is overwhelmingly positive and enthusiastic. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, I&#39;ve seen all this before. Multiple times. This is the hype machine in full force because what is at stake is not the future of mankind - but the price of stock. This is the Silicon Valley hype machine in full swing to drive an investment fever in order to prop up the latest tech Ponzi scheme designed to make VC firms another ungodly sum of money before the hype deflates, and we&#39;re left with yet another set of broken promises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s go back to recent history in tech - big data and the blockchain. Remember them? They were going to revolutionise everything too. They were going to change how we operate as humans on the planet and free us from the tedium of work. It was going to be sunshine and rainbows for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they didn&#39;t deliver any of that. Instead, every government institution went and spent millions on bullshit infrastructure like a &#39;data lake&#39; to still have no idea about their customers, users and staff. They are still incapable of making an informed decision because data doesn&#39;t do that - people do, but we spent all the money on the lake, so now they don&#39;t decide. They don&#39;t function. This isn&#39;t just government. Every organisation has spent the last decade accumulating data to the point where they have normalised surveillance and destroyed any notion of privacy. And for what? The Likes? The Shares? The hits and impressions, the eyeballs and the attention. All of this has rolled into the world&#39;s biggest distraction — the planet is burning up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We became so distracted that we didn&#39;t even question the legitimacy and absolute lunacy of the blockchain. The &#39;trustless&#39; technology that worked out you can Ponzi scheme faster by removing people from the equation. Blockchain birthed the financial institution preferred by criminals and pedophiles the world over, which, as of February 2023,  requires the same amount of electricity as Australia to process just  0.11% of the world&#39;s economic transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hype is the game. The game is all just about money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The product isn&#39;t the AI text of videos - it&#39;s our ability to hand over money to the already rich to allow them to get richer at ever-increasing speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It even has a price tag now - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/news/2024-02-14/sam-altman-7-trillion-ai-bid-openai-chat-gpt/103460282&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;$US7 trillion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this was in my drafts this much richer post &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wheresyoured.at/sam-altman-fried/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Subprime Intelligence&lt;/a&gt; from Ed Zitron was published. I recommend reading it as it contains links and depth that support for the opinion I shared.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Margin Week</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-20-margin-week/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-20-margin-week/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;Margin was the secret sauce that sold me on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/focus-course/&quot;&gt;focus course&lt;/a&gt; in the first place. Shaun discussed and posted about the flywheel of productivity, but also the negative counter-productive wheel as well. What I’d got out of a previous blog post was that I was certainly on one of these wheels, and it wasn’t the good one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/images/flywheel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flywheel of Pructivity outlining the steps of Identify, Plan, Act and Celebrate as well as it&#39;s inverse - Busywork, Reactive, Procrastination and Burnout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last few years had slowly spiralled out of control, and I found myself lost in busywork, being completely reactive, prone to procrastination and having repeating bouts of burnout. I needed to change, and what was coming out of this course was some of the mechanisms to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were introduced to the &lt;strong&gt;7 Areas of Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;, which were set out as common impediments to change because they undermine our ability to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inbox addiction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Urgency mindset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distractions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Counterfeit rest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Busywork&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perfectionism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inbox Addiction was a key one for me. This isn’t confined to email, but our tendency to check our online life and dip into the firehouse that is the modern social feed. I’ve become pretty dependent on my phone as a tool for distraction, scrolling around at every pause in daily life. This clip came up in one of those feeds somewhat surreptitiously:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?height=476&amp;href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Freel%2F756032806384688%2F&amp;show_text=false&amp;width=267&amp;t=0&quot; width=&quot;267&quot; height=&quot;476&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness. Yeah I guess that’s what it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Urgency Mindset was in regards to prioritising &lt;strong&gt;urgent&lt;/strong&gt; over &lt;strong&gt;essential&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a behaviour that I have grown into and with sober expense when it comes to my health and wellbeing. I’ve struggled with getting my priorities right, more so my decision making when it comes to my priorities. Essential are things like exercise, family time, relationships and networks, but not giving them the attention they deserve because of whatever is on fire or due tomorrow is not good. I need to address this better this year and have started to mark out some key boundaries at work and set some more realistic expectations for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest the whole list applies to my life at the moment and it’s why I’m here! Out of the remaining items I found the idea of Counterfeit Rest quite interesting. True rest is the kind of activity that &lt;strong&gt;give&lt;/strong&gt; you energy rather than take it. I’d actually started to think about this a bit earlier having read something similar. At the end of most work days my brain felt like it was fried and so rest became a mixture of scrolling on my phone and watching shit TV. It didn’t make me feel more rested, in fact it probably made me more tired and more distracted. All I was doing was adding more inputs into my already stretched brain. More inputs, more options, more choices = more distractions. But if I spent the same time playing guitar or writing some code or editing photos, or writing – then I felt better. I felt that even though I&#39;d given something of myself, more had come back in return. Rest wasn&#39;t just about sleep, but a more holistic practice of &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;recharge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Given our electric lives I think we spend more time and effort ensuring our devices can recharge more than ourselves!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This area of my life needs some more work. There is a lot of solidly built up habits that revolve around my phone and I need to break that habit, but I need to come up with some better practices. This is on my to-do list and I&#39;ll probably write up something if I find some that work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next exercise got us to jump into our Urgency Mindset. I really liked this quote from Stephen Covey included in the workbook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urgency addiction is a self-destructive behavior that temporarily fills the void created by unmet needs. And instead of meeting these needs, the tools and approaches of time management often feed the addiction. They keep us focused on daily prioritization of the urgent. […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to realize that urgency itself is not the problem. The problem is that when urgency is the dominant factor in our lives, importance isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This concept of &lt;strong&gt;urgent&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;essential&lt;/strong&gt; was really clarifying for me. The definitions used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urgency is usually defined by &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;external&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things that are essential are fundamentally important, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;regardless&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; of external factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a lot of ways the simplicity of this is to focus on the meaningful aspects of life — your health, wellbeing, family and relationships - as these are essential to life. Everything else isn&#39;t as important because its not essential to our lives. We can argue that our jobs are, but in reality work might be or an income, but not our jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urgency, therefore is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;relative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; while essential is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;absolute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it was on to Margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Margin is breathing room.&lt;br /&gt;
It’s the opposite of overload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea of space and capacity is central to the concept of margin, and to be honest, I could feel that. At work, I felt like I was sprinting all the time, but the race I was in was a marathon. This meant fatigue and burnout were not just inevitable, they were guaranteed. Without space to rest and recover, I was going to degrade over time. It was already happening. My health wasn&#39;t great, my family time had been distracted, and my ability to care had been challenged. There wasn&#39;t space for everything, so I was pushing out the essentials and had replaced them with the urgent. I needed to change that around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meaning around Margin itself was essentially&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Margin is the space between our load and our limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This required a bit of unpacking from my perspective. I couldn&#39;t tell you what my baseline load was, nor my limits. For years I&#39;ve just been operating without thinking. Working in a field with knowledge rather than physical labour, finding and accepting those limits was challenging. I have a drive to do more, to do it better – but I can&#39;t do everything, and that&#39;s the only limit I&#39;d found – not everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this wasn&#39;t sustainable and bordered on the absolutely ridiculous. There were hard limits if I looked. One was simply what I got paid for – there are only so many hours in a week that I get paid for, so all work has to fit into them. If it doesn&#39;t, then it&#39;s not my problem to solve. I needed to prioritise what was important at work, what were the essentials vs the nice to haves. Completing my timetable in the habits week helped me deal with the biggest constraint in life — time. There&#39;s no way to create more of - just to spend less time in specific areas. Time wasn&#39;t the only area, though; there were a couple of other areas in life that needed margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creative/Mental&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next challenge was to create margin in each area in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing our capacity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decreasing our load.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing our capacity essentially was around ways to raise our limits and how much we can take on. We could do that through a number of practices such as intentionality, routine, deep work, discipline, saving and strengthening. Decreasing our load was looking at ways we could automate, eliminate, delegate, set boundaries, have self-control and focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for each area that&#39;s what we did - come up with a way increase our capacity and decrease our load. Doing this we would restore margin into our lives (or at least craft a path to do so).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for me I chose the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Time&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;↑ planning the week and month ahead&lt;br /&gt;
↓ creating clear boundaries at work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Finances&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;↑ create some new income streams&lt;br /&gt;
↓ spend less - no new big expenses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Emotions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;↑ more time outside with family&lt;br /&gt;
↓ less time wasted scrolling around feeds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Creative&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;↑ switch off my devices and find a flow state&lt;br /&gt;
↓ less time wasted scrolling around feeds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Health&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;↑ more exercise and physical activity&lt;br /&gt;
↓ less bad food&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might notice a bit of a double-up on the scrolling around - but I feel that insidious behaviour is impacting a couple of key areas of my life and that it&#39;s taking up too much of my attention (despite the fact I do it to escape!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Focus Declaration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final part of the course was filling out our &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus Declaration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The statement drew on a bunch of the activities we had completed during the course and summarised what we achieved. So here is mine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I value &lt;strong&gt;understanding&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;independence&lt;/strong&gt;, I want to focus on my &lt;strong&gt;career&lt;/strong&gt; and begin moving toward my desired outcome of &lt;strong&gt;being able to have a choice in the work I do&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that small, consistent steps can result in big change. Thus, I will begin to make time in my schedule for &lt;strong&gt;developing a side hustle&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to protect my ability to focus, I will work to restore and maintain margin in my &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt;, by &lt;strong&gt;planning the week and month ahead&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;creating boundaries at work&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signed&lt;br /&gt;
TIM KLAPDOR 17/2/2024&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a little longer to finalise the last week and return to my Focus Declaration, but I actually appreciated the extra time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in the end — would I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefocuscourse.com/Course/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The Focus Course&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, 100%. I&#39;ve started to use a lot of the techniques in other areas of my life, and I&#39;ve come back to my notes on numerous occasions. I feel better about work and life. I&#39;ve made peace with some critical aspects of my job and have really enjoyed embedding some of my habits. I still need to break my phone addiction, but at the same time, the device has let me complete a few of my habits. While I&#39;m yet to publish much on learning design, I have been writing and creating words (via text-to-speech) using my phone. I&#39;ve found the commute to be incredibly productive as I&#39;ve shifted to taking the train every day rather than driving. Increasing my outputs rather than my inputs is my happy place, and I feel like I&#39;ve got traction and am moving in the right direction. I actually feel like I have a focus that I haven&#39;t had in years — not just on the everyday, but on the bigger picture too. I know more about what I want out of life and what I want to achieve, which feels empowering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, do &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefocuscourse.com/Course/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;the course&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Habits Week</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-19-habits-week/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-19-habits-week/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/focus-course/&quot;&gt;focus course&lt;/a&gt; started with a list of any current habits or routines we had - both positive and negative. I had some good routines at work with my team, which I&#39;d developed and worked on to establish and set them up. Some of my chores had a rhythm - being the cook for the household helps. Getting our dog made daily exercise a strong habit; without it, he would go mental and take us with him! But apart from those, I found I had a lack of positive habits. There were many negative ones – getting on the phone, not planning anything for the weekends, mindless scrolling, playing time-eating games. These were often focussed around escape - trying to get away from work or the mounting chores and tasks at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step was to develop ideas for habits, routines, systems, and activities across the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/6-areas-of-life/&quot;&gt;6 Areas of Life&lt;/a&gt;. This was really about how to align these with our own vision and values. The next step was to pick those up and pick a single activity for each area and map out the required time commitment and frequency of the activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having gone through the previous weeks and become much more aware of my goals I actually found this to be much easier than I expected. So my habits that I wanted to add in were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spiritual &amp;amp; Inner = &lt;strong&gt;Nature Time&lt;/strong&gt; of 2 hours and to do this weekly. This activity will move me toward my inner personal goal of connecting to place because it&#39;s time away from screens. It is time to engage with beauty and feel the weather.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical Health = &lt;strong&gt;Hard Sweat&lt;/strong&gt; for 1 hour a week. This activity will move me toward my physical health goal of feeling confident to take on more challenging activities because it will push me harder, and I earn rewards from the effort and a feeling of achievement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationships = &lt;strong&gt;Phone a Friend&lt;/strong&gt; for 1 hour a week. This activity will move me toward my relationship goal of connecting with people because I will actively connect with old (and new) friends and build regularity of catching up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rest and Recreation = &lt;strong&gt;Plan the Week&lt;/strong&gt; for 1 hour a week. This activity will move me toward my rest and recreation goal of taking time for me to create margin and space because I need to be conscious of my time and make better use of it — not treading water or being reactive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Career = &lt;strong&gt;Write and Publish about Learning Design&lt;/strong&gt; for 2 hours a week. This activity will move me toward my career goal of creating value and a reputation because it helps create business opportunities and a sense of giving and fulfilment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finances = &lt;strong&gt;Side Hustle&lt;/strong&gt; spending about 3 hours a week. This activity will move me toward my financial goal of starting a new business because every step towards this goal gets me there faster and will make me feel more in control of my finances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step was putting them on a weekly planner and seeing how that would all work. There were a few things I went and added to my planner so as not to make this idealistic - but something that would be possible to do. So I included my work hours, commuting, walking the dog, chores and cooking time, and some other areas of life I felt were missing from my schedule - family time and date night. It&#39;s not that I&#39;d miss those, but I wanted to include them on my schedule as &lt;em&gt;things I need to do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so I didn&#39;t get around to writing this up straight away. It&#39;s been about three weeks, and I&#39;ve been living the schedule, and it&#39;s working! I&#39;ve managed to follow it. Getting to the gym has been challenging since coming back to work, but my work schedule has been pretty up and down, and we&#39;re getting into a bit of a flow with the new family schedule too. What I&#39;ve noticed is that the general pattern of life feels good, not overwhelming. I&#39;ve had time to myself and have been progressing toward all of my goals which is a great feeling. The habits are working!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Broken Streak</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-12-broken-streak/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-12-broken-streak/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I also didn’t close my green circle - the exercise ring on the Apple Watch. I was pretty tired by the end of the week as the new work schedule kicked in. The dog had a play date so my regular exercise didn&#39;t quite happen. I went to bed early, and right as I was heading off to brush my teeth, I looked down, and my exercise ring wasn&#39;t quite closed. I could have put on my shoes and headed out around the block and closed that damn circle, but I didn&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/images/streak.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Gap in My Streak&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, I&#39;d think that this was a failure, but to be honest, I&#39;d forgotten to rest. In all my planning and trying to be more focused on the future, it&#39;s all been about doing things and getting things done. I keep pushing down rest as being idle as wasteful, but it&#39;s something I have to be more conscious of and pay attention to. I think I need to schedule rest and idle time just to add buffer and recovery to my habits. Rather than ignore it, it’s more about making space for it - to be conscious of it and that it is a rational need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also made me think about the gamification trap many of us have fallen into. Some of that data is really good and motivating. Those streaks have helped move my inactive body into an active one. I&#39;m seeing results from the health data from the changes I&#39;ve made to diet and exercise. They help quantify change. They also don&#39;t tell our story. They don&#39;t understand the long haul flights or travelling, illnesses or sick kids that mean exercise isn&#39;t even an option. I appreciate the prompts sometimes; they help chores become habits, but they lack nuance and awareness, which, if they were truly &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot;, they would understand.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dualities</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-11-dualities/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-11-dualities/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;Music is a big area of this curiosity and expression. I am drawn to the more complex music and often find myself drawn to hybrids and fusions of styles, tastes and sensibilities. I grew up playing metal throughout my teenage years, which in and of itself plays into the nature of dualities. Here is a whole genre that toys with dualities - of being brutal and beautiful, emotive and reflective, layered and simple, funny and hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently came across Four Stroke Baron via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/progmetal/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;r/progmetal&lt;/a&gt; on Reddit. They play a heady mix of heavy progressive metal and new-wave sound that is quite unique. I&#39;ve had their songs on repeat for a lot of this year so far, coming back to the haunting sonic scape of [Cyborg Pt.II: The City](&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/7scFocWRan0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/7scFocWRan0&lt;/a&gt; for another hit again and again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning I was poking around online and came across the film clip for another song Sundowner. The 3rd person point of view clips are great (I was blown away the first time I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WXs8XwHGuWg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Lok står när de andra faller&lt;/a&gt;). What I love about this Sundowner is how it captures this clip captures the duality of the song. There is the fun and joy of the opening riff and vocal line, but the song soars and changes throughout. It descends and rises, is dark and joyful - and the transition between these dualities is beautifully captured in this tiny transition in the first minute of the song.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:56%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/r273IbLr99BCduXbxw&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameBorder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/sundowner-fourstrokebaron-r273IbLr99BCduXbxw&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love these little moments in songs and film, and this little clip gives me such joy. The ability to transport you between time and place, space and emotion is jarring and the shock is like a little shot of adrenaline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can enjoy the rest of the song here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;responsive-iframe-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/YqTrMbxs50w?si=QT6tCOKqqpqCU2a6&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>January 2024</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-01-january-2024/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/02-01-january-2024/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h3&gt;The Vibe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vibe has been chilled. I&#39;ve had pretty much all of January off from work, which has provided some much-needed rest and space to think. It&#39;s been a staycation - half planned, half because of circumstances (wife with COVID and some financial constraints). At the end of 2023, I was probably heading towards another burnout. I think I had two episodes in that year alone, but this time, I recognised the signs and, with my leave approaching, was able to switch off and not go down that path. Christmas away with family was a quick defuse of the situation, but I felt that I wasn&#39;t really present for my family during that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;January kicked off back at home — with a plan to eat better, exercise and get my shit together. Part of getting my shit together was enrolling in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefocuscourse.com/Course/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Focus Course&lt;/a&gt;. I came across the course via a blog post earlier in the year that discussed the busted flywheel that leads to burnout -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://thesweetsetup.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/symptoms-of-busted-productivity.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This really resonated with where I&#39;ve been at work for the last year, but maybe longer. It does describe where I get to in terms of work and life at my lowest points. I don&#39;t suffer from depression - but this flywheel perfectly describes me at my worst. It&#39;s great being able to recognise something, but I needed to make changes. With two weeks of the focus course complete I have gone back to look at my core values, articulated a vision for my life that I feel good about, and started to work on some goals. This all ties in to making some changes to diet and exercise and I feel much more mentally prepared for the new year. The sense of impending burnout has gone and now I feel more focussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still two weeks of the course left, so there is plenty more to do, but my next big step is to feel more practised. To embed the changes into my everyday life. The challenge comes from going back to work and school and the drumbeat of the everyday returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the gym has been good. I do enjoy doing something more physically engaging and feeling better connected to my body - which often feels more like a flesh suit my brain is wearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I have been thinking through and working on has been to create a side hustle, something that I can challenge myself with but also open up some new possibilities. I&#39;ve spent the last 7 years working on designing better learning experiences and I&#39;ve created a bunch of resources and processes to do that. My plan is to build on that over the year and create some opportunities to share that. I&#39;m hoping to have a starting point up online in the next month... so keep an eye out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of my favourite snaps from the month.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; data-footer=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/timklapdor/albums/72177720314386151&quot; title=&quot;2024&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53492461793_0b2ce46b3d_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;2024&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Recommendations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on what I&#39;ve been watching, reading and listening to I&#39;d recommend the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Watch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Once Upon a Time in Northern Ireland&lt;/strong&gt; - A harrowing documentary told through historical footage and interviews. It reminded me of lunchtimes I had while working up in the north of Ireland and living in Derry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/z7DuvWVazpk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;fascinating video&lt;/a&gt; on Australian vowel sounds. A lot of the technical stuff is over my head, but I love that you can accurately describe these very nuanced aspects of language and sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Binged on &lt;strong&gt;The Bear&lt;/strong&gt; S01 and S02. It&#39;s an interesting mix of themes and vibes, it has a &#39;feel good&#39; tone while dealing with really traumatic themes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beef&lt;/strong&gt; – Interesting story, great characters and premise. I loved the final episode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mr Bates vs. The Post Office&lt;/strong&gt; was an interesting portrayal of events in the British Postal System where Post Masters were blamed and held liable for software accounting errors. I can see a lot of similarities with Robodebt - and also what the next round of AI applications will be like. We have been warned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O.J. Made in America&lt;/strong&gt; I made it to E04, the courtroom episode, which was the first time I&#39;d seen the crime scene photos and been exposed to the DNA evidence. That was a horrific murder, and he got away with something terrible. The courtroom events were made for the tabloid media, and shockingly, it was allowed to take place. The final episode is wild. OJ fell off the radar here in Australia and his ending was not something I recall hearing anything about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black Bird&lt;/strong&gt; - amazing series on Apple TV+. Truly great acting and storylines that run the gauntlet between deeply humanising and horrific and terrifying. The power of contrast is used perfectly throughout the series, balancing out the horrific and the beautiful. The pick of the series is The Place I Lie.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Listen&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://darknetdiaries.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Darknet Diaries&lt;/a&gt; - binged this podcast series on cyber attacks and defence. There are lots of really good stories explaining professional skills in more depth, and this matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Read&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://robinrendle.com/the-cascade/012-design-systems-burnout/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Design Systems Burnout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was a nice framing of the idea of systems work. I understand the feeling here about working in a system and the feeling of burnout. But I liked the two articles linked out - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jackcheng.com/sunday/414-all-work-is-care-work/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;All Work is Care Work&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://aworkinglibrary.com/writing/unified-theory-of------&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;A unified theory of fucks&lt;/a&gt; and I can relate to those connections. The reasons for systems work is &lt;strong&gt;care at scale&lt;/strong&gt;. Rather than care as a one-to-one specialised commodity, can we provide greater independence and self reliance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jackcheng.com/sunday/414-all-work-is-care-work/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;All Work is Care Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to call this piece out on its own for its message about work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All work is care work. Not a statement of fact, more an outlook, a mindset. What if you asked, of your tasks and projects, “For whom am I caring?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer can be yourself. That’s a valid answer. It’s often &lt;em&gt;not only&lt;/em&gt; yourself but yourself and another – or more than one another. The reader of the published article or book. The neighborhood. The future children and grandchildren and/or your childhood self. The forest, the planet, all things living.&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
 Maybe true care, even when directed, turns out to be warmly concentric. By caring for one &lt;em&gt;whom&lt;/em&gt;, you’re also caring for many other whoms. Maybe true care has no hard edges; it radiates outward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aworkinglibrary.com/writing/unified-theory-of------&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;A unified theory of fucks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both above articles referenced this piece by Mandy Brown. This is great on a couple of fronts. I liked this description of burnout:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to tell this story, about my theory of fucks. The theory goes like so: you are born with so many fucks to give. However many you’ve got is all there is; they are like eggs, that way. Some of us are born with quite a lot, some with less, but none of us knows how many we have. When we’re young, we go around giving a fuck about all kinds of things, blissfully unaware of our ever-dwindling supply. Until one day, we give the last fuck we’ve got, and we notice that the invisible bag of fucks we’ve been carrying around all these years is finally, irredeemably, empty. We have no more fucks left to give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I liked this more hopeful and engaging description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of my answers to the question of, why give a fuck about work? Why &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; your work? It won’t, of course, love you back. It can’t. Work isn’t a thing that can love. It isn’t alive, it isn’t and won’t ever be &lt;em&gt;living&lt;/em&gt;. And my answer is: &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t give a fuck about your work. &lt;em&gt;Give all your fucks to the living&lt;/em&gt;. Give a fuck about the people you work with, and the people who receive your work—the people who use the tools and products and systems or, more often than not, are used by them. Give a fuck about the land and the sea, all the living things that are used or used up by the work, that are abandoned or displaced by it, or—if we’re lucky, if we’re persistent and brave and willing—are cared for through the work. Give a fuck about yourself, about your own wild and tender spirit, about your peace and especially about your art. Give every last fuck you have to living things with beating hearts and breathing lungs and open eyes, with chloroplasts and mycelia and water-seeking roots, with wings and hands and leaves. Give like every fuck might be your last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because here’s what I’ve learned: if you give your fucks to the unliving—if you plant those fucks in institutions or systems or platforms or, gods forbid, interest rates—you will run out of fucks. One day you will reach into that bag and your hand will meet nothing but air and you will be bereft. You will realize the loss of something you did not know you ever had. But if you give a fuck about the living, about all your living kin in all the kingdoms, &lt;em&gt;they will give a fuck right back.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in and around systems fucks get lost in the system, but there is value in the system if it is about the living. Focus the system on empowering those it touches, that will earn you fucks!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Strategy Week</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-29-strategy-week/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-29-strategy-week/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;Strategy Week in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/focus-course/&quot;&gt;focus course&lt;/a&gt; was all about manifesting our &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-28-vision-week/&quot;&gt;vision and values&lt;/a&gt;. We started out with an introduction to the &lt;strong&gt;8 Laws of Focus&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ownership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Margin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sowing and Reaping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tradeoffs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These made a lot of sense, each one describing a way of bringing things into focus, like whatever the machine is at the optometrists that swaps lenses in and out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then went into the &lt;strong&gt;6 Areas of Your Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Career&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inner-Personal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rest &amp;amp; Recreation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These areas often overlap; what happens in one space affects another, and one goal can help achieve another. The big aim of the week was to take each area and develop goals for different time spans - someday, 5 years, 1 year, 1 month, 1 week and today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was some big thinking, but I felt prepared for it. Mrs K and I had a habit of doing 5 years plans when we were younger. We joked that they always needed to be rewritten every 3 years as we made some dramatic decision that would uproot our lives. We haven&#39;t done that for a long time though. Once you have a partner, house, child and steady job, there is a tendency to stay that way and not be adventurous. For a while, that was good enough, particularly as we dealt with the trauma of &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/the-fire/&quot;&gt;the fire&lt;/a&gt;. Moving to Adelaide was a big move, and then COVID hit, and I am only realising again how traumatic that was. We lived off adrenalin and cortisol for two years, waiting for family to die whilst being at our most remote and distant. We were forced to retreat and disconnect and be unable to connect with anyone new right when we arrived in a place where we knew nobody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was time for some goals!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I jumped the gun on this a little. I had started thinking about this before I really started this week in the course. During my thinking time hiking through the bush, as I pondered values and vision, I also started to think about goals. We have a house (well, a mortgage, at least) - what&#39;s next? I have a decent-paying job - so what comes next? In the next 5 years, where will we be as a family? How different will our situation be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having my values and vision made this task a lot easier, and I really liked working in those different timeframes. It was thought-provoking, but that&#39;s why I&#39;m here. I was able to marry my vision to some clear goals and get some of that clarity and focus I&#39;ve been missing in my life across all six areas without too much hassle. For the first time in a long while, I feel like I made progress rather than just treading water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not going to share everything, but I think my Someday Goals act as a guide to how I&#39;m thinking about the future and how that sits with my values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Area&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Someday Goal&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;1. Career&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Work is optional and I have a choice about it. Rather than dominate life, it becomes an auxiliary function.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;2. Relationships&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Maintain a strong family bond with both sides. Have friends to share travel and adventures.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;3. Physical Health&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To take better care of my body and embody my physical self.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;4. Inner-Personal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To find a sustainable connection to people and place.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;5. Finances&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No mortgage or debts. To have a haven - a place to go for refuge and safety.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;6. Rest &amp;amp; Recreation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To feel I have the energy and capacity to give and be able to choose when and what to give.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They provide a bit to play with in the other timeframes, but I was able to flesh out actionable and achievable goals for each area, which I&#39;m happy about and can work towards feeling better clarity around why I&#39;m doing what I&#39;m doing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vision Week</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-28-vision-week/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-28-vision-week/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am writing up a brief reflection for each week of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/focus-course/&quot;&gt;focus course&lt;/a&gt;. Week 1 was Vision Week, and I was keen to jump straight in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were first introduced to the &lt;strong&gt;5 Components of a Focused Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life Vision - Why&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goals - What&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action Plan - How&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schedule - When&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Habits - System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a flow mapped from each item to the next (1st to 5th), and it&#39;s suggested that if there is a specific problem with one of these components, it&#39;s best to go upstream and find the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This posed a pretty big problem for me... I&#39;d never considered having a Life Vision. Or perhaps what&#39;s more likely is that the key milestones and goals that I set early on in life I&#39;d achieved, and I haven&#39;t ever gone back to revisit those goals. So, I was pretty quickly having an existential crisis! Why am I here? What the fuck am I doing? That was kind of the point of doing the course right - to diagnose what I needed to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So of I went with my trusty dog by my side to hike through the hills and ponder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is my life vision?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the work for the week was to develop your personal values, so I worked through each of the activities, which provided some guidance and asked the right kind of questions, but at the end of the workbook, I wasn&#39;t satisfied. It just didn&#39;t sit correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d tried to cheat a little and use the personal values I&#39;d come up with two years ago during a team building exercise which I repeated midyear in 2023. They felt current and correct then, but then again a lot had changed both at work and at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it was back to the drawing board. My original values were &lt;strong&gt;Understanding&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding still felt correct. It summed up my holistic drive to understand, to learn, be curious, have empathy, be creative and accepting of others. This felt true to the point where I could feel it in my bones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accountability was where the problem was. I think this stemmed from a time and place and a frustration with the lack of accountability at work, in politics, in society — I had figured if I felt so deeply about it, it must be a value I hold true to. In many ways it is, but it doesn&#39;t capture why... why does accountability matter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I returned to the list I had floating around (I&#39;d created a spreadsheet and used scores to shortlist before!). What I wanted was something that was more encompassing of multiple ideals. I was originally leaning towards authenticity, but that wasn&#39;t me; it was almost more of an ask for others. I respect truthful, honest, and authentic people, and I want to be around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I looked back at times I felt good, happy and challenged positively — and I think it comes back to feeling &lt;strong&gt;Independent&lt;/strong&gt;. Having autonomy and being able to be true to myself, honest and open. There is a self-reliance and survival component to it, but I think I also understand the need for help and aid that is required to gain independence — it is something that is worked for and earned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My two values of &lt;strong&gt;Understanding&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Independence&lt;/strong&gt; felt better. They felt right. And so with that, I went back to the tasks, and while I didn&#39;t have to change much - things felt much more aligned than before. With my value in place I could go back to my Vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course provided a simple template for this, drawing on a number of the activities in the workbook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;In my roles as a ———, I want to express, impart and exemplify the values of ———, by ‚———.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was fine for a draft, but I wanted to make a vision a bit more personal to give it a bit more spice and flavour!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is complex, but I want to seek to understand it. That means moving, changing and being dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is experiential. I want to see the world — walk it, taste it, see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be accountable for my actions and seek to tread softly and make choices that are good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want the world to learn, starting with myself, then my family and those I can touch. Through learning, I can create opportunities for understanding, compassion and friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to have independence and help others achieve it so that we can live openly and honestly, being true to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being so zoomed out was such a release and a great way for me to get into that headspace. I was lucky I had the house to myself for most of the week and the time to really indulge in thinking. This summary overlooks a lot of the time and self-doubt I experienced during the week. In the end, it was worth it, and I celebrated with a cold beer on the deck.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Managerial Solutions</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-16-managerial-solutions/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-16-managerial-solutions/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;During one of my many meetings, I pondered,  &amp;quot;What exactly do I do?&amp;quot;. How limited are my actions in this process? I decided to write down what actions I am able to actually implement and came up with this short list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debate&lt;/strong&gt; - bring people together to resolve conflicts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delete&lt;/strong&gt; - remove the task, it&#39;s not going to happen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delegate&lt;/strong&gt; - apply someone else to the task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delay&lt;/strong&gt; - push back the task to a later date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defer&lt;/strong&gt; - put the task on hold until it is required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Double down&lt;/strong&gt; - add extra resourcing to ensure that it gets done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diminish&lt;/strong&gt; - reduce the scope of the task to something that will actually be completed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this list diminishes the role of &lt;strong&gt;experience&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;context awareness&lt;/strong&gt;, as these play a vital role in taking the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; actions, but nonetheless, the possible actions of the manager are very limited. I think this is why being a manager so often feels unfulfilling and can be frustrating. There isn&#39;t a lot of creativity possible within these constraints. Because of that limitation, it&#39;s not very attractive to those with the right experience or context awareness - and this is what breeds managerialism - where those with limited experience and context take on manager roles and proceed to make poor decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2024 - Do and Donts</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-10-2024-do-and-donts/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-10-2024-do-and-donts/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is to lay out the behaviours I want to see from myself and acknowledge the less desirable ones, as well as a way of checking myself against falling down a rabbit hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Dos&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Don’ts&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Develop a sustainable routine and rhythm to the week.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lurch from one thing to the next like a drunk maniac.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sweat every day. I need to work on my fitness and consistently.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Use the weather as an excuse. Match the activity to the weather, one is out of your control.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Focus on career development. Work towards the future.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Focus less on my current job. It’s fine, and you’re already good at it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Move away from the drama. Start to call it out, but don’t buy into it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Get sucked into the drama vortex. Face what’s in front of me not the periphery.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Stop talking, start doing. Start making things happen. &lt;em&gt;Make the future&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Stop over thinking and wishful thinking.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;More food prep. Take the stress out of cooking and make life easier.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The carbs. This is the default solution for a lack of preparation, but it’s not helping at all.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Be more social. Make more effort to go out, to call people and reconnect with friendships.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isolate yourself. I recognise the trauma of COVID and the reaction to seal myself off, but it&#39;s not healthy.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Connect. Find the others. Get out of my shell and meet more people, build a network, find a way.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fall back to what was. That&#39;s still there, but there&#39;s a need to push forward now.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Version 1.0</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-05-version-1.0/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-05-version-1.0/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;So here it is — version 1.0!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been keen to get &lt;strong&gt;Heart Soul Machine&lt;/strong&gt; up and running for a while now. I&#39;ve put it off for ages, wanting time and space to get it all perfect in my head. That lack of action prompted me to just go ahead and build it. Perfection is the enemy of good. 100% of nothing is zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a space for me, not everyone else. I wanted to create somewhere beyond the performant nature of social media. Somewhere social and connected, but my own space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it might be useful to go into a little bit about what is happening behind the scenes of HSM - what is the machine?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site is built with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;11ty&lt;/a&gt; a javascript based &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/performance/static-site-generator/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;static site generator&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;SSG&lt;/em&gt;. An SSG essentially outputs your entire website as static HTML pages. This means you don&#39;t need to run a special web server or maintain a database. I create the content as Markdown files, build out the templates I want and the SSG smooshes them together. I just use the command line to &lt;code&gt;BUILD&lt;/code&gt;, and it outputs a folder full of files I can deploy anywhere. What the SSG does best is allow me to use some basic programming like &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/if-this-then-that/&quot;&gt;IFTTT&lt;/a&gt; style statements to create extra functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m currently hosting the site on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve been a customer of GitHub for quite a while, and while it&#39;s been bought by Micro$oft it&#39;s still performant and provides me what I need. The beauty of a SSG is that the actual files live on my computer. I can back them up and put the site up on any number of services — so I have flexibility built in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve tried to do some new things with 11ty, SVGs, HTML and CSS during the build. For that end I&#39;ve packaged up a few things into the site:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/eleventy-plugin-time-to-read#speed&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;eleventy-plugin-time-to-read&lt;/a&gt; - Adds the handy reading time estimate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/plugins/rss/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;eleventy-plugin-rss&lt;/a&gt; - Added the default RSS plugin. I&#39;ve previously made my own, but XML sucks, and this was a 5-minute job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/kevinweber/pen/dXWoRw&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;SVG Factory&lt;/a&gt; - I borrowed this from Kevin Weber a while ago, and I use it and SCSS to create all the icons you see around the site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/@photogabble/eleventy-plugin-interlinker&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Eleventy.js Interlink Plugin&lt;/a&gt; - I&#39;m an &lt;a href=&quot;https://photogabble.co.uk/projects/eleventyjs-interlink-plugin/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Obsidian user too&lt;/a&gt; and was keen to incorporate one of the best features of Obsidian - Wiki Links! Now, I can use them in the site build without worrying too much about 11ty&#39;s weird internal linking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bnijenhuis.nl/notes/automatically-generate-open-graph-images-in-eleventy/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Social Previews&lt;/a&gt; - I adopted the Social Previews outlined by Bernard Nijenhuis. This creates an SVG for each post and then saves a JPG version of it and adds it to the &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt; of each page as an Open Graph element.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stephango.com/flexoki&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Flexoki&lt;/a&gt; - I&#39;ve been really enjoying Steph Ango&#39;s work and stumbled across their Flexoki colour palette. It actually matched pretty closely with what I already had in mind with my initial sketches for this site. So I adopted Flexoki into my CSS and have been using HTML Variables throughout my CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chriscoyier.net/timeline/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/a&gt; - I didn&#39;t scope this in the initial build, but after I stumbled across Chris Coyier&#39;s site, I wanted to include something similar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stephango.com/evergreen-notes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Evergreen Notes&lt;/a&gt; - Another Steph Ango feature which really resonated. I plan on going through my back catalogue of posts and adding them to the site - but I&#39;m keen to extract the little pearls of wisdom along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Testing the Kia EV6</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-04-testing-the-kia-ev6/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2024/01-04-testing-the-kia-ev6/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;A year ago, over the Christmas break, I rented a Polestar 2 as my first foray into the land of electric vehicles. This year, I was in a similar predicament - a week away from home in Sydney and needing to rent a car. Europcar came to the party this time, adding a raft of new Kia EV6s to their fleet. The car looks great. I like the design and shape, especially the details in the lights and body panels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/images/kia-ev6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kia EV6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our pickup didn&#39;t really go smoothly with Europcar. I&#39;ve done a few rentals with them recently and not had any issues - but when we arrived at 7.30pm there was no car ready on the lot and the only one available had around 50% charge. The fact that I had to book in advance and have the booking confirmed for this specific vehicle meant they knew I was coming and what time I would be there. After enquiring about a charge card or credit, I was informed that it wasn&#39;t on offer - take it or they can allocate a different car. I decided to go ahead and take the one available as we were hungry and keen to get on the road to eat and make a tour we had booked at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sydneypoint.com.au/attractions/sydney-observatory/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Observatory Hill&lt;/a&gt; (which I recommend!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after about 30 more minutes, the car arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d read a lot about Kia and Hyundai as the kings of the EV world, producing great cars with the latest and greatest technology and all the features - fastest charging, big displays, and comfortable interiors. So I had high hopes for this experience. The EV6 is a pretty hefty car. It is probably a medium-sized sedan but sits higher. I was expecting lots of space, and there was in the cabin. The boot, however, was tiny. Our suitcases required a bit of Tetris to get them in and allow the automatic tailgate to close. There is no depth to the trunk at all - it&#39;s flat and very shallow. In the profile pic above, you can make out where the rear bumper ends, just before the brake light swoop. That&#39;s it. The whole boot is that deep, and the height disappears with the rake of the rear window. This is not family car territory and you would struggle with a pram and shopping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shock number two - connecting your phone. Yes, the Kia EV6 has carplay. It&#39;s not wireless, so you need to plug your phone in. There are a myriad of USB-C ports around the car. The thing is - they are &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;charging&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; ports - not &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; ports. There is one USB data port that you need to use for Carplay - but it&#39;s USB-A. Plugging the phone in via USB-C port did nothing. Going through the menus and the phone would connect via Bluetooth, but not via the USB. We tried two cables, nothing – the same issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 minutes into hiring this car and I was not impressed. I was hungry though. So we used the unbuilt navigation to punch in our destination, Millers Point, and hit the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&#39;Driving Aids&#39;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been a while since I&#39;ve driven a Kia. The last time, it was a work car, and I hated every minute of it. The steering was spongy, the performance was less than enthusiastic and the build quality was questionable. I&#39;ve had that experience hanging over me ever since. So while I read a lot of positive reviews about these new EVs, I have to wonder - is it true? Have they changed? Are Kia&#39;s now drivable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first experience wasn&#39;t great. The car beeps, a lot. The nav likes to talk, a lot. Turning on your indicator displays a rear-facing camera on the side you are indicating up on the dash. Late at night on an unlit street, that just means your dash flashes black, and you&#39;re not sure if you&#39;ve broken the car. Your speed is off to the left of the dash, and the dead centre is a chart showing how Attentive a Driver you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the way into Sydney from the Airport, it was sensory overload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to drive was impeded by the complexity of the car and the distractions provided by the multitude of &#39;driving aids&#39;. The car beeps, the steering wheel tugs, the nav warns of an impending school zone, speed limit change, camera, lane option — and all I want to do is concentrate on driving in Sydney traffic and make sure I&#39;m going the right way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Zombie Mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is a thing. There&#39;s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/xywCVMkvxCM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; and everything. This was the second time I&#39;d turned on the car and .... nothing. The car came on, but I couldn&#39;t drive. I couldn&#39;t change gears, put it into drive, nothing. My wife pulled out her phone and started Googling, finding the video above fairly quickly. But to have hit this issue on the second time in the car did not bode well on my overall experience so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;It is an EV&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, I got out the manual, worked out the USB issue with the help of my mother-in-law&#39;s handy cable and got Apple Carplay running in the car. Now I could use the navigation I was used to, the display I was used to and concentrate on the car to drive with. I set up the seat and driving position better. I tried to get the Heads-Up-Display (HUD) working, but couldn&#39;t for the life of me adjust it to fit my preferred driving position. I&#39;ll admit I am all torso and ride high in the seat, but nothing abnormal or that a taller driver wouldn&#39;t encounter. Back on the road in daylight and the indicator cams made sense (to some degree). Yes, I can see behind me, but I&#39;m looking down to do so - my eyes off the road and what&#39;s in front. The cameras also don&#39;t show anything that I can&#39;t see from my mirrors. This seems like gadgetry for its own sake. The HUD is the same. If the layout of the dash was improved there is nothing I would need from this. Having the current speed on display is nice - so put it in the middle of the dash!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those frustrations aside, the EV6 is an EV, so you get nice immediate throttle response. The car is heavy, but heavy low to the ground so corners are easy and there is no body roll. Its flat and fast if you want it to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The car comes in three modes: Eco, Normal, and Sport. These seem to be configured in a slightly non-sensical way. In &lt;strong&gt;Eco&lt;/strong&gt;, the steering is heavy and the throttle mundane; it forces you to drive more conservatively in a very heavy-handed way. &lt;strong&gt;Normal&lt;/strong&gt; is just that, normal and how you would expect the car to behave. &lt;strong&gt;Sport&lt;/strong&gt; is an odd sensation. The throttle becomes super light and responsive, perhaps a bit too responsive. Alongside that, though, the steering also becomes much lighter. It means you can certainly throw the car around a bit more, but with the super-sensitive throttle, this is set up for a disaster. I did punch the throttle hard at one point and could feel the rear wheels kick out a bit. I almost over-corrected because the steering was too light. In a &#39;normal&#39; sport mode, everything becomes stiffer, so you get better feedback on the drive. Sport in the Kia is more akin to &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Fun Mode&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; – and I&#39;m not a fan of that. It&#39;s what a lot of people will do, but in a way that&#39;s not about the driver or driving the car well. I think Kia has really missed a beat here - but it&#39;s probably a choice that will be popular and reflects the popular concept of Sport rather than the reality of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Charging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with the car starting at 50% charge there was a need to charge it. I took the opportunity to head to the closest fast charge and see how it went. The Evie 150kw charger has two bays per &#39;bowser&#39; and will split the charge across the number of cars. I arrived at an empty charger and watched as the car maxed out at 150kw and then ducked out for a beer. The car was at 100% within 30 minutes. I thought I might have a bit longer, but no, this thing sucks down those electrons much faster than the Polestar 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comfort&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EV6 is comfortable. There is oodles of space in the rear seats and the front seats are comfortable. Over the Christmas break we did a lot of ferrying of people and it handled it with style and comfort. The ride is nice, the performance of the car is great and so a lot of the shortcomings I had about Kia were forgotten. This is the best Kia I have driven and it&#39;s a great car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a big car, but not overly practical. If your primary aim is driving people around – you&#39;re in luck. It&#39;s spacious and comfortable. But if those people have stuff – then you&#39;re in for a shock. There&#39;s not a lot of boot space. There is no hidden compartment or any usable space in the &#39;frunk&#39;. Then there&#39;s the price. The EV6 is not cheap by Kia standards. It&#39;s not cheap by general car standards. This is an expensive car – and I&#39;m not sure it suits the price tag. The materials are more &#39;plasticy&#39; and the &#39;velour&#39; seat fabric wasn&#39;t my favourite. Nor were the white accents on the back seat. I can see this car looking very used very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, &#39;driver aids&#39; were more gimmick than useful, and some of the basics just weren&#39;t done well. The dash layout being the prime example and the UI for the whole infotainment felt dated and the menu system and settings were located in unintuitive spaces. If you want to charge the premium price, the experience has to reflect that. I wouldn&#39;t buy this. I wouldn&#39;t recommend it unless you&#39;re after an Uber vehicle which is unlikely to take anyone to the Airport, because the minute someone turns up with a suitcase it&#39;s going to be a hassle.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2023 - A Wrap</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/12-31-2023-a-wrap/"/>
    <updated>2023-12-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/12-31-2023-a-wrap/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;2023... WTF was that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year felt crazy. It felt like there were a lot more down points this year as plans and projections kept failing and falling over. A lot was happening at work, and that&#39;s where most of my energy was drawn into. There were a couple of  highlights though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fiji&lt;/strong&gt; - We had a great week in Fiji. There was a bit of drama, but it was such a good break during winter in a beautiful and friendly place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port Lincoln&lt;/strong&gt; - My wife and I headed to Port Lincoln to do the shark dive - jumping into a steel cage to see real-life Great White Sharks in their natural habitat. We saw four different sharks on the day! We spent the other days exploring the local area, the two national parks and some amazing sights and fresh seafood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Birthdays&lt;/strong&gt; - My mum&#39;s 70th and brother&#39;s 40th birthdays were this year. Mum&#39;s was a big family event and the first in a few years. It was great to see all the cousins and nieces all together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduation&lt;/strong&gt; - Seeing Ms A graduate from primary school. It&#39;s a much bigger deal than I remember, but it is a significant milestone for her and us as parents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a couple of work highlights too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colombia&lt;/strong&gt; - I gave an online presentation as part of the federal Department of Education &amp;amp; Training&#39;s initiative in South America. I did one last year for Brazil, so was aware of the bi-lingual nature of the event and what was involved. There were over 350 people in attendance on Zoom, which I was super impressed by.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ACODE LTLI&lt;/strong&gt; - A week in Queensland in August is never a bad thing. This institute was a lot of work and effort, though. It was great to get out of my bubble and meet a bunch of new people, as well as get to know my colleagues from Adelaide better during our downtime.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Change at work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was tremendous change at work, with the bulk of it starting in February and dragging out until August. I watched my career trajectory, or at least the way I imagined it going, crumble in front of my eyes. All the work I&#39;ve been doing over the last three years seemed to be leading to a specific point, and it seemed to be all on track. That all got completely derailed pretty early in the year, and I spent the rest of the year spinning. Rather than having leadership that steadied the ship and provided clear direction, we seemed to have the opposite — management keen on disruption for its own sake, an inability to communicate and unwillingness to engage their teams, under-baked ideas, no plans for operations and an obsession with adding more and more instability and momentum to the spiral and spin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;December has come, and my previous career path has disappeared in front of me. I&#39;ve felt increasingly angry, disrupted and troubled by this. I guess it is part of a grieving process, and I need to be comfortable with that being what has happened - grief. There was something clear and tangible that has taken away. There has been a loss, and it seems right to grieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t think I&#39;m alone in experiencing this, but it&#39;s probably the first time in my life I&#39;ve felt that I wasn&#39;t going in the right direction, not just in an upward direction but in general. Much of the effort I have put into things hasn&#39;t been rewarded or, honestly, even recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Knowledge Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my problem is making space for this grieving process to happen, to re-evaluate my position and make some decisions. One of the fundamental challenges of &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/knowledge-work/&quot;&gt;knowledge work&lt;/a&gt; is it involves your brain and thinking, which means making space and separating work and life is incredibly challenging. I found the two inexorably linked and that both were affecting each other. The problems at work bled into home life. The time needed to think ate into family time. I find this difficulty of knowledge work to be different from manual labour, especially when the job requires a machine or a specific location to do the work. Separation becomes easier if it is physical; there&#39;s a clear demarcation point in the day between work and family. At the end of this year I&#39;ve been completely exhausted all of the time. My brain is done and I haven&#39;t been there for my family or able to engage in the other pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the week off I&#39;ve had so far - I can see there needs to be some pretty fundamental changes in 2024. I want to spend the first few weeks of the year working through that. I have to really reevaluate this whole work/life balance concept, but the focus needs to be on &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crisis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve probably hit that midlife crisis point in terms of my career. I have started to ask myself that fundamental question — &lt;em&gt;what am I doing?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#39;t really enjoyed going to work this year. I don&#39;t think work should make you sad or angry. The culture has changed significantly over the last year and it hasn&#39;t made it a pleasant place to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said the people I work with and those that I have recruited into the team are amazing. One of the positives of the year has been the fact that I&#39;ve spent more time collaborating across teams and areas. That&#39;s been incredibly fulfilling and I honestly think if that hadn&#39;t happened this year would have felt a lot darker than it has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A new plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&#39;s time to evaluate where I am and where I am going. Luckily, I&#39;ve got time to do that over January as I&#39;ve taken four weeks off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up to my 40th birthday, everything was looking good. We made a big change moving to Adelaide and taking on new jobs. Covid hit and that&#39;s had a much bigger effect on my life than I thought. There&#39;s a trauma that we&#39;ve gone through over the last few years that still hasn&#39;t been processed. So much changed - not just from the lockdowns, but how we interact, who we interact with and the confidence to get out there. Covid was such a big disruption and such a big traumatic event that life returning to normal really means now its normality wrapped around the trauma and isolation that occurred. It&#39;s not a return to &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; but &amp;quot;normal + trauma&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can feel now a deep need to connect. I don&#39;t think I&#39;ve spent a lot on the other things outside of work — individual pursuits, connection opportunities, socialising and networking. Work has been a leech on my energy and it&#39;s had a real parasitic effect on my wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, instead, I want to put effort into those spaces that give me energy and to seek out more joy and positivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s to 2024!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What becomes of Australian Rugby?</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/09-28-what-becomes-of-australian-rugby/"/>
    <updated>2023-09-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/09-28-what-becomes-of-australian-rugby/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week, the Wallabies lost to Wales and ended their World Cup run. It was probably the worst match I&#39;ve seen the Wallabies play. That&#39;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It. Was. The. Worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who watched the Ireland vs. South Africa game on the same weekend, that was a game on another level. If you watched the way the Fiji team played against the Wallabies, you could see it there too. The difference was the sense of national identity and way of playing the game. There is a distinct Irish, South African, Fijian, French, and Kiwi style of play. Attached to that is a national pride in their game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A loss and a win born from that distinct way of playing is bearable. There is pride in playing that style of game regardless of the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wallabies haven&#39;t had this for a long, long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot wrong with the state of Australian rugby, its governance, structure and operations that have compounded this issue. But at its heart, Australia has no game, no style and nothing distinctive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is symptomatic of Australian professional sport in general, which has prioritised the brilliance of individuals over the team for so long that we’ve forgotten what a team is and what it has to do in order to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to save rugby one of the most important things we have to do is articulate &lt;strong&gt;what Australian Rugby is and what it looks like&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last 20 years, we have adapted the game to suit the players we can put on the field rather than build a specific identity around how we want to play the game. What that means is a completely incoherent message for players and fans: as availability, injury, and age of players change, so too does the game itself. As we swap out yet another underperforming coach, we destroy any stability or coherence that had been building. Every coaching change for the last 15 years has just patched over the deep cracks within the game itself. More important than the game is this national identity of &lt;em&gt;what we want the game to be&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;What it can be&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The All Blacks, Springboks, Irish, Welsh,  Fijians and French all have a clear identity of what they want the game to be and how they want to play it. And what that means is that there is a clear baseline of expectations. There is a default way of playing that these teams can fall back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas the Wallabies fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see it in the smaller nations, like the Chileans, the Samoans, and even the Romanians - there is a way of playing this game that they&#39;ve grown into and they love it. And love is what’s missing from the Wallabies. There is little to love about the way we are playing the game. Yes, there are individuals who can exhibit brilliance in every game -  it’s far from a team effort, and it’s far from consistent. The hero of one game becomes the villain of the next. As tactics change and teams adapt to those individuals so goes our fortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than dwell on what went wrong, I think it&#39;s time for us to have a bigger discussion about what we want rugby to be and how we as a nation want to play it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not to undercut the problems with the organisation and at the grassroots - but we’re never going to solve those until we can articulate what rugby in Australia should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting this vision right ensures that all the required changes and what must be built to strengthen the game have a shared purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting down the foundation of the game that we want to see will attract the right players and coaches. It will aid rather than hinder recruitment and talent development. We’ll spend money in the right places on the right players with the right skill set to play the game of rugby we want to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I want to see?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running rugby&lt;/strong&gt; - we have always had some of the best running players on the planet. We all want to see Aussies with the ball in hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tries&lt;/strong&gt; - I can take a loss on penalties if we go for a try every time. Aussies want to see the ball across the line or die trying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tactical kicking&lt;/strong&gt; - playing the game from the 9 does little for running rugby or the kind of kicking that encourages scoring tries. A rush defence has holes in it which a kicker can exploit. The 50-22 rule is made for attacking and tactical kicking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contested breakdowns&lt;/strong&gt; - we have a history of the best jackaling forwards in the game. This kind of bastardy is the best kind of defence and should be our first line of attack. We’ve forgotten the art and mongrel we once had in this space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attack, attack, attack&lt;/strong&gt; - there is something about the Australian mentality that prizes attack over defence. We want our team to attack at every opportunity, which means every contest. This isn’t just about what we do with the ball, it’s what we do when we don’t have it. We have to unleash the mongrel and fighting spirit of Australia. This isn’t about being the underdog but about being the dog and choosing to take the fight to the opposition at every opportunity. I’ll take any loss, no matter how bad, as long as we contest and attack at every opportunity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More than a one-trick pony&lt;/strong&gt; - As a team, we have to be able to adapt to tactical changes. We need to have more than one game plan, and we need to be able to adapt to change within a play or two rather than 60 minutes later when the game is done. That means better on-field decision-making and more tactical team coaching - not the reliance on individual brilliance we have seen. We have become the most tactically devoid team on the planet, and it’s been the source of many losses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem we have is not the quality of the players; it&#39;s that we don&#39;t play as a team, and we don&#39;t play as a nation. We don&#39;t take risks because we fear failure. We don’t play cohesively because we don’t play as a team with clarity of visions and purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of this comes back to how we’ve structured our domestic teams. Rather than reflecting a distinctive national form of the game, each state franchise that feeds the professional game plays an entirely different style of game. To expect these players to form a cohesive structure and style of play is ridiculous. This starkly contrasts New Zealand, where the teams play a cohesive Kiwi game with slight variations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have to do better, and it starts with creating a vision for what we want the Wallabies to be and how we want them to play!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hello blog</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/09-26-hello-blog/"/>
    <updated>2023-09-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/09-26-hello-blog/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hey there blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while and I’ve been neglectful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life has been going on at a pace and with speed. Work has been crazy. As we discuss a University merger there’s been a reorganisation, a new team structure, the loss of an old team and a reprioritisation of work. Not at my choice or behest, but so it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve struggled with this round of changes, and I had to question myself about that. I feel like I’ve always been working on the edge of change, in that ambiguous state between new and old. If I’ve worked in the innovation space for so long, where I live and breathe change – why has this time been different? I think I understand it now, but it took a while to work through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large part of my experience has been around grief. A lot of what has happened has been the end of things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The team I originally joined is gone. We’ve been disbanded and repackaged beyond all recognition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The team I assembled anew and recruited for has also been changed beyond recognition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The manager who hired me went on to pursue something new and ended up leaving the institution completely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of the projects that I’ve been leading have finished – successful in their outcome but without acknowledgement or celebration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the work I’ve been doing hasn’t evolved in the way that I expected. I imagined riding the wave of developing these new online programs through to a more senior role. I poured a lot of myself, energy and time into that idea and outcome. But things haven’t worked out that way. Decisions have been made, or not, to pursue things in differently – one that doesn’t seem to include me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And my grief is connected to that. That loss of professional self, one that I’d been working so hard towards. From moving to a new city to working through the pandemic to going through the stress of hard deadlines and deliverables, to trying to manage the toll on my team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve wondered if the effort was worth it. I’ve played through the “What ifs?” I’ve asked myself why and come up blank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spawned grief over my effort and my time. I now acknowledge that there was a huge waste of effort. A lack of acknowledgement of what has been achieved has rubbed salt into the wound. The lack of recognition of the expertise I’ve spent years developing has been hurtful. Recognising that the organisation doesn’t care has been challenging. I’ve cared. I’ve probably cared too much. But the organisation doesn’t have feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 360° review demonstrated how little care there was. How little appreciation and recognition had been shown to all that work. I focused too much on getting things done that I didn’t see the impact that was having on me, or how others perceived me. From my team, peers and managers — I barely lived up to my own expectations, and I certainly didn’t see much recognition of what’s been achieved. But this is something I’ve been dealing with for a while – the invisibility of my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve felt frustrated at work for most of this year. Frustrated and ignored. When the future is a version of what I’ve just spent four years working on — I expected to be acknowledged and included in the decision-making. Instead, I was ignored. I get that not everyone has been on the same journey, but when you’ve been the pioneer, trailblazing and encountering all the ‘firsts’ – you’d think the organisation might want to hear about that. To learn from it. I guessed wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I fumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I smouldered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then it went out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That frustration just left one day. I accepted what was, and what had been, but now is different. I can make this what I want to be. Nothing has made it better. I don’t think anything has changed at all — except me. The one thing I can control and affect and change is me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s the aim. To stop doing what I was doing because it didn’t work. To look towards opportunities and to create my own. To embrace change again. What happens will happen, and regardless of how things have been perceived — I know the truth. I know what I did, what I achieved and what came out of those actions. Even if no one else can, I can see it and I’ve felt the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Your Audience Awaits</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/07-23-your-audience-awaits/"/>
    <updated>2023-07-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/07-23-your-audience-awaits/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/07-07-social-to-antisocial/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;quick post on some thoughts about the launch of Threads&lt;/a&gt;, which was a way for me to articulate one of the things I&#39;ve loved about joining the Fediverse – the really &lt;em&gt;social&lt;/em&gt; nature of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A week or so on, and Threads is up to 100 million users, and there&#39;s been plenty of hot takes and commentary posted. I won&#39;t be joining. I don&#39;t want Meta in my life any more, and I only stay rooted to it because many friends and family have no alternative online presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the commentary, what I have picked up as a giant &amp;quot;plus&amp;quot; is that it&#39;s simple and easy to assemble an audience. Many people joining from Instagram inherit the same followers in this new space. And many people want that. Journalists, critics, and media personalities want an audience — that is why they are on social media. It&#39;s not about the &lt;em&gt;social&lt;/em&gt; aspects - it&#39;s the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s not what you get in the Fediverse. There are no followers ready to go. There is no easy way to aggregate people into an audience or disseminate your work. There&#39;s no algorithm to boost you or pay to promote you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From discussions in &lt;a href=&quot;https://megaphone.link/VMP4819911436&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Pivot&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/07/06/podcasts/special-episode-metas-twitter-rival-arrives-with-adam-mosseri.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Hard Fork&lt;/a&gt; — the benefits of Threads is the pre-built audience you have. The fact is the whole application is gamed around giving you an audience. It&#39;s also what brands want, what advertisers want – let&#39;s remember that the launch of Threads is not a life raft for those seeking refuge from the ever Right-leaning and sinking ship that is Twitter. It&#39;s about recruiting those advertisers and revenue. As Twitter tanks, there&#39;s a lot of money to be made by those who are ruthless to jump in and provide a viable alternative with the same goals at heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;pullquote&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audience = Money&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it – that&#39;s what Threads is: the cannibalisation of Twitter&#39;s audience and advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to say that this whole &amp;quot;distributed&amp;quot; social network thing isn&#39;t real. Threads isn&#39;t distributed or federated. BlueSky isn&#39;t either – there are no other instances, nor is there any operability available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no real effort from Meta to do anything new or embrace new technology – it just saves them from developing their own. They can avoid contributing anything to establishing a standard. Instead, they pick it up straight away – throw a few hundred engineers at it, and make the technology behind real federation - like Mastodon - look unwieldy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A gap is going to open up between this next set of apps and those currently forming the entirety of the fediverse. One side will be open, the other will focus on an &lt;a href=&quot;https://timklapdor.wordpress.com/2015/11/26/social-media-a-story-of-exploitation-enclosure-and-enslavement/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;enclosure&lt;/a&gt;, trapping users into an ecosystem and audience they can&#39;t leave behind.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Social to Antisocial</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/07-07-social-to-antisocial/"/>
    <updated>2023-07-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/07-07-social-to-antisocial/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Threads&lt;/a&gt; has launched, and now Facebook (aka Meta) has entered/reentered the fractured social space created by Musk&#39;s Twitter. People are rushing to the platform, mainly because those inside the Facebook realm on Instagram have a zero-friction signup. What is perhaps not noticeable to most of those people is their passive agreement to intrusive surveillance and advertising. At nearly 250MB for what is essentially a text reader, you have to wonder - &lt;strong&gt;what have they packed into that code base?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I wanted to note some ideas about what social media means and perhaps what it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; mean as we enter a new phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is that social media, as we understand it today, wasn&#39;t ever really social. It wasn&#39;t about creating social spaces or communities; it was only about leveraging existing social networks and relationships to sell your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook&#39;s original premise wasn&#39;t connecting the world - it was a game of &lt;a href=&quot;https://mashable.com/feature/hotornot-history-20-year-anniversary&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Hot-or-Not&lt;/a&gt;. It used existing social networks and university campuses, not its own unique ability to connect people to create an audience. It played into the social psychology of young people but offered little social return or value. Instead, the company&#39;s value became the audience it provided, not the social connections or ability to find and form relationships. It provided eyeballs, and all it asked you to do was perform. It wasn&#39;t to communicate; that&#39;s too boring, and people leave the app and go on with their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, here you had to &lt;strong&gt;perform&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media has only ever been social in name. It pillaged your existing networks and communities to harvest data to build a graph &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; owned. &lt;em&gt;Your&lt;/em&gt; relationships became &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; relationships in an instant. Platforms never encouraged or even enabled dialogue. What they enabled was simultaneous monologues that fit the model of performance. A social space without dialogue is not social – it is antisocial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And every platform followed the same model — insular, monologic, performative, ad and surveillance driven, and increasingly toxic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the Fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This small cluster of apps using a shared protocol began to retake and carve out a social space built upon social ideals like federation rather than centralised control. Each space could be its own community, but its participants had the ability to connect with others outside their own space. Communities could also put walls up – exclusion is part of feeling connection - and the fediverse created a multitude of ways to engage in that practice. Things were porous but there were layers of safety and protection available. What the Fediverse didn&#39;t provide was an audience. It didn&#39;t reward performance, and that&#39;s helped keep it sane and real. It&#39;s why many haven&#39;t joined too. Without a pre-made audience, what is it all for? That question is valid for those who have built a career and reputation based on their audience and their ability to engage with it and perform for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That barrier of not having an audience has allowed something different to grow and flourish in the Fediverse, something that feels more social and more communal. It isn&#39;t divorced from conflict or harm, but the scale and performative value of attack is greatly diminished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there was Threads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s too early to say what the impact will be on the Fediverse, but it won&#39;t be good if it shares any of the platforms&#39; attributes before it. The massification it offers is not a positive for the Fediverse. The nature of all things Facebook is driven by performance and audience rather than any true meaning of social.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Connected Curriculum</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/06-25-the-connected-curriculum/"/>
    <updated>2023-06-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/06-25-the-connected-curriculum/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the last four years, I’ve been overseeing the development of online programs at the University of Adelaide, and for the past 15 years, I’ve been involved in the development of courses, programs, media and assessments and aligning those things back into curriculum and program design, constructive alignment and accreditation requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the problems that I’ve seen consistently during that time is that each one of those components has its own separate workflow, ways of working and related data. None of these elements connect, talk, link back or feed into each other. They also share a similar disconnection – time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most curriculum is developed linearly with very few feedback loops or iterations in the process. If feedback exists, it&#39;s usually measured in years, not months or even semesters. Most data and artefacts remain static throughout the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Program information is usually developed at the very beginning of the process. If any changes happen when a course is developed, it rarely feeds back into that original documentation. There are often important reasons for making ad hoc changes that add value to courses, but there’s no facility to track what they are, why they happened, or measure and see how they impact things at the program level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we could connect data about the curriculum throughout its development?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if instead of static documents, we utilised data throughout the workflow – to not only map out a program but to help detail what and when specific skills and knowledge are not only introduced but developed and applied too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/connected-curriculum/&quot;&gt;Connected Curriculum&lt;/a&gt; would provide a way to engage with learning design across a program through courses, assessments and potential specific activities and tasks. It would allow us to set parameters for learning at a high level and, as a course is developed, demonstrate and show when and how that learning develops, where students engage with concepts and how they go about applying them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could also map accreditation requirements not just to courses but to individual tasks and assessments. If those assessments are linked to the LMS, you could pull examples of students’ work across the grading scheme from live courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than just a map of possibilities, as you create courses, you could feed up information about the student experience into the program view live and as it happens:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time have students spent on specific activities?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have they done group work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have they completed specific accreditation requirements?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When and what is the evidence they have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is that this is completely impossible today because the data model doesn’t exist. The modularity of programs, courses and hours is not specified correctly. One can’t zoom in if the detail isn’t there. There is no “&lt;em&gt;enhance&lt;/em&gt;” button that provides data that isn’t there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/connected-curriculum/&quot;&gt;Connected Curriculum&lt;/a&gt; isn’t new, but it is still missing from most organisations working within education. While many aspects have been standardised and now require accreditation, much of the process is still opaque. It’s hard to visualise because of the atomisation of education and ed-tech – where many tools exist to perform ever-specialised teaching functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I can see how it could work. By creating a flexible data model, a clear link between course and program could be made. Using simple tools, like tags and standard nomenclature and a modular approach to course design, it’s not only possible but holds the potential to be a breakthrough in creating higher quality courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently completed a round of work on some program mapping and then applied this straight into course design, and I can see how useful a &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/connected-curriculum/&quot;&gt;Connected Curriculum&lt;/a&gt; would be. Having created capstone courses for programs that I had nothing to do with developing, I can attest to how useful a &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/connected-curriculum/&quot;&gt;Connected Curriculum&lt;/a&gt; would have been. Having gone through accreditation processes before, I can see how important a &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/connected-curriculum/&quot;&gt;Connected Curriculum&lt;/a&gt; can be – and how much work it requires when it doesn’t exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, this is just an idea, but I can see how it connects to some of the work I’ve already done. A way to connect program design to learning design in more tangible and visible ways would be incredibly powerful for institutions to have and for the staff working across these areas. It would help empower academics and designers at all levels to create better student learning experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Work Heroics</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/06-18-work-heroics/"/>
    <updated>2023-06-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/06-18-work-heroics/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h3&gt;My Work Heroics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These heroics have been an asset in a lot of my work. They encourage my creativity by engaging with problems and seeking solutions. For projects that are off the rails or find themselves in dire straits or all good conscience will fall over — I come along and rescue them. I plug holes, I pull together resources, and more often than not, I throw myself into the breach. As an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultureamp.com/blog/expert-generalist-workplace&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;expert generalist&lt;/a&gt;, this encourages and feeds my broad skill set. So, for many reasons, this is a positive for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for the last couple of years, it hasn’t felt that positive. When problems are occasional, this heroism can be useful and rewarding. For the last couple of years, it’s been a hindrance. The projects I’ve been working on have been new initiatives. They don’t have a playbook and a track to follow. Resourcing was a guesstimate, and much of what I&#39;ve spent my time doing could be considered &lt;em&gt;known unknowns&lt;/em&gt;. There were always expectations that we wouldn&#39;t have issues or that problems would arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, rather than the exception to the rule - problems have become the rule. In the beginning, we joked in the team that fires were always springing up. You put one out, and another would sprint up. For the last 18 months, it&#39;s felt very different — everything is on fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:900x500/1200x800/filters:focal(450x250:451x251):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/6438793/this-is-fine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the comic strip from KC Green – &lt;a href=&quot;http://gunshowcomic.com/648&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;This is fine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I can see now is that while the heroics got things across the line and helped create success, they did nothing to reduce many of the underlying problems. Many solutions happened at an operational level through dialogue and conversation because most of the problems were human. Therefore, most of the knowledge about this work was tacit. It never had to be written down or documented. In fact - a lot of the heroics were to prevent things from &lt;em&gt;becoming explicit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work was done to prevent deadlines from being missed, overcome or remove problems, and work with staff so complaints and issues weren’t filed or issues logged. My work really has been so focused on patching over the cracks and delivering things that are of high quality and timely that the projects &lt;em&gt;look flawless&lt;/em&gt;. All of the structural deficiencies don’t show up. I applied the fix before the break has been noticed. I’ve been the hero again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now I’m tired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to address the underlying issues and have not really had the success I anticipated. I seem to have been met with a “Problem? What problem?” reaction. All the work I’ve poured myself into is invisible to everyone except those it directly affects. I’ve had some fantastic working relationships along the way, which has been great. But relationships are invisible, too. So much of my work is intangible, the effort of thinking of a solution to a problem, the mitigation of an issue so that it doesn&#39;t happen. If the organisation doesn’t see it, it doesn&#39;t really matter. It doesn&#39;t care about relationships, even though it likes to say it does. There&#39;s lots of talk about &lt;strong&gt;Stakeholder Engagement&lt;/strong&gt; but very little about dialogue, discussion, compromise and understanding - all tacit components of getting things done. The explicit, Have a Meeting, is more important than the tacit, Achieve a Result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There might be a case for making my work more explicit, &lt;em&gt;but that changes the work&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There might be a case for letting things fail, &lt;em&gt;but failure has consequences&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you let things fail when you don’t have to? Do you continue playing out the trolley problem when the emergency brake is right there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This heroic mindset probably grew from a habit of procrastination. Work that I don’t find engaging gets left to last. Rather than being planned and methodical, I opted to be fast and dramatic. Last-ditch appointments, late nights, last-minute saves - it becomes a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My early career was in small businesses where a fuck up would not just lose me a job but close down a business. My heroics probably got more formalised in this environment. I came to expect it from myself. I could make impossible things happen. I could move a mountain. And I felt I needed to. There was a duty and pride wrapped up in &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; letting things fail. I could save everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing enough superhero lore, I can see all of this being played out by Marvel and DC characters in comics and movies. Maybe that’s why I enjoyed Ben Affleck’s Batman - there was a distinct “I’m over this shit” vibe that resonated with me. There&#39;s a limit to the heroics, and it gets to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it, though — I don’t have a solution. Just a description of the problem. I can’t seem to perform heroics on myself.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Two to one, or maybe something new</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/04-10-two-to-one-or-maybe-something-new/"/>
    <updated>2023-04-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/04-10-two-to-one-or-maybe-something-new/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s not a secret, there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adelaide.edu.au/creating-a-university-for-the-future/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;plans for a merger of two universities in Adelaide&lt;/a&gt;. At the moment, we’re in the proposal stage, investigating the viability of the merger and developing a business case for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a number of perspectives, there is a case to be made. Most of these relate to being too small to operate globally. While that may be true, it does make me question whether the purpose of a university has changed so drastically over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Universities in Australia are a function of each individual state and not of the national federal government. They are brought into being by an act of state parliament, and while there is an operational distance, they are a public service run for and by the state. The way the merger is being articulated at the moment sees the contribution of universities quite differently. They are now an “exporter” of education, bringing in a billion or so dollars into the local economy from international students. It’s also being framed as a grow house for the next generation of research and skills required by an ambitious military program. These two components are seen as drivers for change and form the basis of merger discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, South Australian universities are too small to be recognised internationally and would fare far better on rankings across the board if we merged. This would lead to a proposed increase in student numbers to drive that export function and increased research funding because our reputation would rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I’m not unsupportive of these moves, I wonder if they signal a fundamental shift in how we see ourselves. They are certainly a shift from local concerns and push the university&#39;s role into a global realm, one we might not all feel comfortable joining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also makes me wonder how this approach informs decision-making moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Risks and Opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s play out the fact that the merger will go ahead. I think it will because the appetite is there to make it happen - the only way I see it being halted is cost. The universities are working away feverishly to pull together a business model before the state government. Part of that will be to gold plate the plans and ensure there are enough golden parachutes on offer for those at risk of losing their job - there will not be two Vice Chancellors. So let’s just say it happens, I think there are a couple of different ways you could set this up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elimination&lt;/strong&gt;: going through the catalogue of services, systems and products offered by the two universities and choosing the “best” one to continue. This is probably the quickest and ”simplest” way to proceed. Simple, as in the choice is binary rather than multifaceted. It’s faster because of this in the short term, but it is incredibly risky and challenging. Systems tend not to work together just because you want them to. There is a lot of tacit knowledge embedded in staff around how things work, and uprooting that creates its own challenges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amalgamation&lt;/strong&gt;: going through the list and merging features from both institutions. Taking longer than elimination, this would be the development of a “best of breed” approach to products and services. The complexity of this approach is that it requires consensus around what “best” looks like. Best is often an emergent and multifaceted property that depends on the individual&#39;s perspective and priority. While this way of working has a lot of people and process challenges, this is an opportunity. Consensus onboards people during the process rather than after. It also can be done quickly if facilitated well - but given existing university practices and a history of death by committee, that is a challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-creation&lt;/strong&gt;: taking the knowledge of both institutions to reimagine their functions and ways of working. This requires more imagination, but it starts with a clean slate and asks “what if…?”. Given the size and scale of change, this might seem daunting, but re-imagining and recreating the university as a new entity is a massive opportunity. If you want to discard some of the legacy and deadwood accumulated in the system and structures, now is the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I can see that, in most cases, a mixture of the first two will be adopted, I want to make a case for Re-creation and spend some time there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unbundled from the inertia of existing models, re-creation is an opportunity to change how and why we do things radically. It’s an opportunity to be radical and unencumbered. It offers a massive opportunity to be creative and sets the new institution apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the time for &lt;strong&gt;Radical Ideas&lt;/strong&gt;. Something new is on the table, and I don’t think it is time to shy away from radical ideas. Instead, we should be seeing them out. One of the biggest problems I see in the merger discussion so far is a lack of differentiation. How will this University be different? How will it be unique? Moving to be more relevant to a global audience means entering a crowded marketplace. You have to have something different to sell. You have to have a value proposition, and at the moment, I don’t see one other than the geographic location. It’s the same degrees offered at every Australian institution, following the same basic structure, using the same tools and teaching techniques in almost identical rooms. What is it about Adelaide University that’s different?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, here are a couple of ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Set a unified curriculum.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curriculum is one area you could differentiate quite easily. The curriculum is ripe for disruption because most universities lack a clear and unified vision. It’s murky and messy and often relatable for students. What drives students is the qualification, not the journey they go on or the road they take. Mainly because they don’t know it’s there in the first place, but also because it relates too much to over-ambitious and vague motherhood statements. What if, instead, we made the basis of our curriculum something more real and tangible? The &lt;a href=&quot;https://sdgs.un.org/goals&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;UN Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/a&gt; are real and formally agreed to, not by a bunch of white guys but through global collaboration. They provide clarity of mission and a diverse portfolio of ideas that set a bigger mission for higher education. Aligning with the SDGs sets the University up on the global stage as a way to participate and contribute to their development and longevity that benefits the world. This aligns with the global vision of the new university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Turn costs into income.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade, one of the most innovative actions I’ve seen is when organisations turn costs into income. Renewable energy is one of those, where instead of paying for power ad infinitum, installing solar and wind provides power and generates income. It&#39;s a capital investment, but universities are designed to be here for the long term. So what if we apply this idea to other areas? One that Is ripe for disruption is IT infrastructure. At the moment, universities spend ever-increasing amounts of money on IT systems, and that cost is only set to rise. As Cory Doctorow points out, platforms (and, more broadly, businesses in general) follow a pattern of &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;enshittification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, they are good to their users; then they abuse their users to make things better for their business customers; finally, they abuse those business customers to claw back all the value for themselves. Then, they die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most universities have benefitted from sharp pricing for IT services across the board, leading to the disestablishment of internal IT services in favour of those provided on the cloud. Software and hardware as a service have seen most universities eliminate on-site internal servers (the ones that formed the original Internet) and move everything into the cloud. The same can be said for student information systems and the learning management system - all cloud-based and monopolistic. Almost every University now spends millions of dollars annually as a tax to Microsoft and AWS for hardware and a handful of software vendors to run their core business. Without spending that money, the University could not exist. They are now trapped into paying this indefinitely, and because the competition has been eaten up over time, we are now in a monopolistic vice. Over the next few years, we will see the vice tighten, and the costs rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to exit this state is to escape it entirely. Applying the same ideals as renewable energy - what if the new University set itself up to run independently as a sovereign entity, not reliant on 3rd party vendors and their costs? What if it embraced open-source software and collective hardware, not just as a consumer but as a contributor? What if it then sold those services and knowledge to others? Aligned with the SDGs, this could create a global powerhouse of development that would directly improve the University, the globe and the local community. This could start a new industry and sector in the state, which aligns with several defence objectives. This is how AWS started - a cost centre transformed into an income generator. Universities consume so much IT yet contribute little back to the broader community in positive ways. This could change all that while creating a new EdTech sector based here in Adelaide but with a global outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reimagine jobs and work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most significant changes and challenges over the last 20 years has been in the work required by a university and what jobs are needed to do it. As universities have scaled up, the requirements on staff have changed. The traditional role of the academic as a researcher with a side gig in teaching is nothing more than an antiquated memory. It no longer exists, and nor can it. The requirements have changed so dramatically - volumes for teaching are massive, research requirements border on ludicrous, and the administration required to run a modern university is off the charts. The academy of old is no more and needs to be rethought and reimagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To cope with the seismic changes in academia, a new and substantial change has occurred alongside it - the rise of precarious work. To allow the academy to continue with its role, it has filled the gaps with ever-increasing numbers of casual staff. We are now operating in a world where most university teaching is carried out by casual staff, surviving contact to contact on barely sustainable wages, with holidays or sick leave and no career progression available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s also the commensurate rise in professional staff - those required to manage and ensure things are done, even to a minimal degree, in a way that marries the requirements of operating a large-scale and legislated industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work at the University needs to be reimagined. We need to lose the current structures that hide the workers and the jobs to be done while at the same time maintaining a system of power and benefit for a chosen few incumbents of the system. We need to rethink work and how to balance it with life, health and prosperity. We have to move away from models of extraction and exploration. We must be fair, free and sustainable in our approach to work. To utilise technology not as a system of oppression but as a way of gaining freedom. To look at jobs as things we want to do rather than a crushing requirement to sustain life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be visionary, be real.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Universities have earned themselves a reputation for operating in ivory towers. Much of what happens within higher education is distinct and separate from the rest of the world. Now is not the time for that. I would love a new University to be explicit with its mission to engage with local problems, to ground research in community issues and to develop knowledge to aid and understand our local communities. Whilst a global perspective is important, we have to see universities as places that are embedded and serve their community as a primary purpose, but with connections that ensure we are situated within a global network. This doesn’t require us to focus on a specific field of research but instead ground it in our own communities. Make it relatable, connected and involved rather than aloof, disconnected and abstract. The UN SDGs would help with that as a way to focus efforts, but being grounded in local initiatives is critical. We must maintain the global perspective while at the same time supporting the lands we stand on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learning is life.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Australia, we have been steadily moving towards a problem the US has been struggling with for the last two decades - how to balance getting an education with living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the face of it, this shouldn&#39;t be something we should consider. Still, the financial realities, the cost of getting an education with current wages, job insecurity and a fragile economy mean that education is becoming a choice rather than an expectation. When students have to choose between a lifetime of debt and insecure work vs the same wage but without the obligation, education will be the loser. The value proposition of higher education has been diminishing over time. We must accept our role in contributing to student debt and failing to engage with students holistically beyond their learning and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a new university, we should be thinking more holistically about our dealing with students. One way to do that is to offer an all-encompassing undergraduate experience that combines learning, accommodation and work. Rather than competing priorities, what if we ensured that they worked together? The acts of living, learning and work all actively contributed to and benefited each other. As students, we created a whole life experience, ensuring that they had the space to grow and learn as individuals in ways that benefit their future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One simple way we could do that is to recognise that the university requires labour, and students can (and already do) play a role in that. What if we formalised that, planned for it and ensured it fed into a broader experience?  We could offer flexible learning arrangements if we allowed students to speed up and slow down their studies. To make it &amp;quot;seasonal&amp;quot; and ensure sufficient breaks in learning for other things to occur. This could reduce most students&#39; mental strain and give them time to gain additional skills and knowledge tangential to study. They could be involved in university projects to enable research and support our global mission, and most importantly, they would be paid to do this. By planning this more holistically, we can make learning with the new university far more beneficial financially and as citizens actively contributing to their community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learning is lifelong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education shouldn’t be terminal and end in a degree. As more and more work shifts to knowledge work and as individuals who are more likely to switch fields and careers throughout our lives, we have to move towards an ongoing education model. One that can be accessed throughout our lives rather than as a one-off. We actually need a model of lifelong learning. In some ways, this may not always be about access to courses but the resources, libraries, facilities, networks, and research that universities contain. What if we made the university a porous experience? One that you flow through repeatedly as your life and career change. You can move through and engage with the University in various ways, and it is priced accordingly. Whilst many have suggested a subscription model, that is certainly part of it, we need to understand that there will be periods of active and passive engagements, so it must be a model that can change and adapt to different stages in life. We need differentiated products that support this model and tiered pricing that not only covers costs but, importantly, instils value. In this way, we can move to a funding model that is less reliant on the ebbs and flows of government but one that aligns with our students and aids them in developing into citizens. It is moving to create ongoing and committed relationships rather than the &amp;quot;one night stand&amp;quot; equivalents we currently have.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Heirs and Hierarchy</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/03-07-heirs-and-hierarchy/"/>
    <updated>2023-03-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/03-07-heirs-and-hierarchy/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve written about hierarchy a few times and often relate it back to being the default structure. The reason I believe this is because it’s a &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt; structure. It’s something that can be deployed quickly, works fairly efficiently, and can be established and refined as you go along. It&#39;s a &amp;quot;good enough&amp;quot; system of organisation well suited to deployment in simple problem spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the other reasons that hierarchies are a default is because it’s a power structure with its own power dynamic. For those at the top, the hierarchy is really beneficial. Along with the power to decide, comes wealth in a variety of different shapes and forms. Therefore, hierarchy is often a desirable form and structure despite how well it functions as a system of organisation and if it is performant in its duties. If something innately enables someone and gives them power, there’s a reason to not only deploy a hierarchy but to maintain a hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listened to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techwontsave.us/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Tech Won’t Save Us&lt;/a&gt; podcast with &lt;a href=&quot;https://techwontsave.us/episode/155_the_untold_history_of_silicon_valley_w_malcolm_harris/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Malcolm Harris&lt;/a&gt;, which discusses a very different history of Silicon Valley than the narrative that we often get told. The topics discussed were numerous and diverse - from eugenics, racism, nuclear weapons, myths of hippies and anti-authoritarianism, and some retelling (with added truth and context) to the stories many of us are familiar with. It is an absolutely fantastic podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of listening, I was triggered to think about hierarchy, not as the default, but because people want it there. There are those who believe hierarchy is a &lt;em&gt;requirement&lt;/em&gt; and a &lt;em&gt;preferred state&lt;/em&gt;, something they are willing to invest time and effort into establishing and continuing. The history that Harris provides around Stanford is just this. A story of those seeking to set up a new and alternative hierarchy, one based on some particularly nasty ideologies. It’s also a story of their success and how their narrative has come to dominate global discourse and trends. Harris also points to this story being a great lesson on myth-making because, despite the claims of being a hotbed of counter culture and antiauthoritarianism, Silicon Valley was and is built on the militarism of the US in the global arena. Every missile and drone is powered by the chips and software developed in and by Silicon Valley. The technology we use every day was developed and funded under a regime that was not counter-culture; it was &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; culture. It was powered by an ideology based on dominance and dominion, not free love and peace. Much of the fragility in global supply chains we see today was brought about by the shift to globalisation and offshoring work, which was pioneered in Silicon Valley to skirt US labour laws and from having to deal with unions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other key idea I drew out of the podcast was the idea of &lt;em&gt;hiers&lt;/em&gt;. It wasn’t enough to establish a hierarchy; it had to continue and in order to do that, you had to breed your successors. This is where Stanford fits in. It was established and still is, the incubator for the next generations of leaders in the hierarchy. But it&#39;s important to remember that the incubator of their heirs is based on the underpinnings of eugenics and breeding practices tested on horses at the Palo Alto Stock Farm. Not only was this group of people able to establish new power based on the West Coast away from the dominant familial lines of the East, but they also established a way to continue their lineage and ideology. While perhaps not entirely concerned with the genetics component, Stanford has become a tool for indoctrination into a way of seeing and understanding the world – one that is often completely at odds with the rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This disconnect is why no one has &amp;quot;innovated&amp;quot; a solution to hunger or homelessness. Despite having the “greatest minds” and access to infinite amounts of capital, Silicon Valley refuses to engage in real problems, mostly because they see inequality as a functional part of the model, not as a problem. You can’t have a hierarchy without someone on the bottom. You can’t compete if everyone is on the same level. You can’t have anything resembling a meritocracy (despite their prescribed belief) if it’s not what you know but who you know. Stanford and all in its shadow thrive on the inequality of hierarchy, and they will go to all ends to ensure that it continues. And they have bred generations of disciples to their ideology — that this is the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I struggled with the thought that hierarchy was problematic because it was the default method of organisation. What we lacked was imagination for how to do things differently to better suit the way we need to work, particularly in complex domains. The problem was the difficulty in moving anything forward while laden with the inertia of what is easy. Now I can see that there&#39;s another element here: desire. Some people don&#39;t want change because they seek power. Or that they feel they deserve it. It is their right. That part of the problem is that moving beyond the hierarchy is a challenge because the power it bestows won&#39;t be relinquished. That change can only come from prising it from their cold dead hands, and even part of the hierarchy is that there&#39;s an heir apparent, just waiting to step in. Moving beyond the hierarchy is not a change that can happen within an organisation but can only be done by replacing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Complexity of Learning Design</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/02-01-the-complexity-of-learning-design/"/>
    <updated>2023-02-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/02-01-the-complexity-of-learning-design/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about learning design as a profession, the kind of work it is, and what we do, and trying to map it to the domains of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/cynefin-framework/&quot;&gt;Cynefin Framework&lt;/a&gt;. This is to help explain what we do as a team to others in the institution and to look at what structures would support our work, especially in an environment of scaled-up development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cynefin Framework contains four domains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complicated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chaotic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things in the &lt;strong&gt;Simple&lt;/strong&gt; domain are, for better words, simple. It’s essentially an easy-to-follow process from input to output, with the process being both knowable and controllable. This simplicity usually applies to the process, not necessarily the tools or technology used, so much manufacturing can fall into the simple domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Complicated&lt;/strong&gt; domain requires many more steps in the process. It relates to very complicated work with many steps and stages, but it is still knowable and controllable. It can be helpful to think of the Complicated work as tasks that can be programmed; it might include &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/if-this-then-that/&quot;&gt;if-this-then-that&lt;/a&gt; statements and for-loops, but it can be mapped and has a predictable output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Chaotic&lt;/strong&gt; domain, on the other hand, doesn’t behave predictably. In many cases, the actors, objects and actions aren’t even clear. Inputs don’t necessarily equal outputs. Things don’t make sense, and it’s very challenging to map out what&#39;s possible within the domain with any clarity or reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leaves us with the &lt;strong&gt;Complex&lt;/strong&gt; domain. Many actors and forces exist in the Complex domain, and their effect on outputs isn’t predictable. This inconsistency in output is the key to understanding the Complex domain. While a process might be knowable and, in some cases, mappable, even to a programmatic level, how things influence and affect one another isn’t predictable. Small changes can have significant consequences. There are many points of potential behaviour. How things may or may not interact and relate isn’t predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there’s a clear reason for this unpredictability - &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work that involves groups of people tends to reside in the Complex domain because people themselves are complex. They are individualistic, organic, adaptable and unique in their skill sets, knowledge and behaviours. Every facet of a person will have different impacts on how they work, behave and contribute. So it&#39;s not just that the process is complicated; when you add people into the mix, they create variation, which creates complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the reality of Design as a practice and profession – with Learning Design being an application of design practice to a specific context (like web or graphic design). Design is the kind of work that is suited and required for the Complex domain because its nature is to creatively adapt and problem-solve to a change and work with variables and constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at some of the factors that Learning Designers have to work with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alignment to the course and program learning outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different delivery modes and models of teaching and learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technologies used to deliver the course as a whole and every interaction and activity within it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The need to plan and development of lessons that aid student&#39;s learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help develop content in various media based on each media type&#39;s affordances and constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review the effectiveness of lessons in student learning based on the application of psychology and learning science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edit copy and ensure consistency of terminology across a course and multiple authors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage production timelines across multiple teams and media types.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure aesthetic principles are adhered to across the course and program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop universally accessible content and activities for students across devices, access levels and physical capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop assessments that provide evidence of learning that is engaging for students and can provide a spread of marks that reflect student&#39;s different abilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align the course to the institutional graduate attributes and professional qualifications based on external bodies&#39; requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of government standards and practices related to the course and program specifics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To that list, you have to add in the roles that they are required to interact with throughout the development of the course:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject matter experts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Course authors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Media production teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video producers and editors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Program coordinators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project managers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team managers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their peers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professional bodies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each factor and each person involved in the process requires not just an action but an &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;inter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;action. That interaction might produce the necessary outcomes and outputs - or it might not because people are Complex. They might be stressed, not in the mood, be sick, with family, hungover, unprepared, or short of time - there are thousands of ways each individual could be affected by their lives and what is going on outside of work, let alone what happens within the job!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Complexity I’ve just outlined is for &lt;strong&gt;just one course&lt;/strong&gt;! When you multiply that complexity across multiple courses, a team, a program of study, and faculties and departments, you add multiple complexities. These multipliers of complexity create a relatively new and unique environment to manage. It is an environment with no levers of control and no direct way to manipulate outcomes. Management relies on relationships, negotiation and compromise - elements that traditional management structures struggle with. Within the University environment, where hierarchy reigns supreme, it is a fundamentally different and often incompatible way of working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is why the Cynefin framework is such an important tool - by identifying the domain you are working in; you can adjust your ways of working and the common practices and structures to match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where I’ll leave this post. I want to discuss the challenges of working in the Complex domain and unpack what it’s like to manage a team and a range of projects in that space. I’ve also got some suggestions for improving our ways of working in the Complex space to help feed into institutional and management discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Testing the Polestar 2</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/01-13-testing-the-polestar-2/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/01-13-testing-the-polestar-2/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I test-drove the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.volvocars.com/au/cars/xc40-electric/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Volvo XC40 Recharge&lt;/a&gt; - their first foray into electric vehicles and the only model locally available to test drive. As our petrol prices ballooned over the last 12 months, I’ve been seriously thinking about making the switch, and with my current lease running out, it seemed like a good time to switch. With a lack of available cars in the country and the inability to test drive many variants, I thought it best to hold off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we started to look at travel plans for Christmas, the prices of things began to add up. Rental cars have skyrocketed in expense, going from a couple of hundred dollars to a couple of thousand. I shit you not that the Holden Barina compact was at the low end of $2500 from some companies. Doing a bit of research, I found that Hertz had invested in a fleet of EVs and that this could be an opportunity to test out an EV over a period of time. So I bit the bullet, and my Christmas present to myself was to plonk down the money for two weeks with a Polestar 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;WTF is a Polestar?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have more than a passing interest in cars - I love to drive and keep abreast of what’s out there. So, I already knew Polestar was a performance workshop that merged with Volvo and has subsequently turned out its own brand of vehicles. A Polestar is essentially a Volvo in its underpinnings but styled and set up in its own unique way — which honestly differs quite a lot from its parent company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.carexpert.com.au/crop/1600/1067/app/uploads/2021/11/POLESTAR-2-LRSM-29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explaining who and what a Polestar is has been a daily experience pulling into parking lots and chatting with family. I guess this is the lived experience of owning a niche brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What’s it like?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To look at, it’s a slightly odd high-riding sedan with a fairly wide and flat profile. The colour is - a bit of a mystery. It’s kind of a grey colour, but it seems to have tints of blue and lilac, depending on the lighting. The car&#39;s lines are fantastic and give the car a sense of speed while demonstrating a solid stance. Big wheels and really nice LED lights around the car finish off a fairly impressive-looking car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.carexpert.com.au/crop/1600/1067/app/uploads/2021/11/POLESTAR-2-LRSM-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An oversized central console dominates the inside of the car. It creates a bit of a cockpit feel for the driver, with a large touchscreen at the centre – about the size of an iPad. There aren’t a lot of buttons to play around with - most controls are shifted to the centre screen. This might seem like an issue - it&#39;s just something you need to adapt to, but after a couple of days, you can set things up quickly and efficiently, even when driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carsales.com.au/editorial/details/polestar-2-carsales-car-of-the-year-2021-finalist-132642/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://editorial.pxcrush.net/carsales/general/editorial/polestar2_magnesium_020-5gcm.jpg?width=1024&amp;amp;height=682&quot; alt=&quot;Polestar Interior&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a love/hate relationship with this centre console. It&#39;s big and eats up a lot of cabin space. There may be practical reasons for its existence, but it reduces leg space for those who like to man-spread and offers little practical storage. There&#39;s a little shelf for your phone, which needs to be plugged in for Apple CarPlay to work, a single cup holder and a console lid that opens up to - another cupholder. There are a couple of hidden shelves on both the driver and passenger sides for small items - wallet or glasses case. The door pockets are also not particularly practical - unable to hold water bottles vertically, which is a bummer. So upfront, there&#39;s not oodles of space for accoutrement or expected needs - like two cup holders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the &#39;cockpit&#39; feel is excellent as a driver. I like the seating position and the way you feel inside the cabin. Everything is well made, with great textures and feel to everything you touch - from the steering wheel, seat fabric, steering wheel, levers and buttons. As the driver, you always feel in control of the car, and everything you need is accessible. The car&#39;s design isn&#39;t open and airy - it&#39;s more closed-in and cocoon-like. Visibility is limited but in a focused way – you see what you need to see. The setup of the mirrors and the additional sensors give you a complete sense of what&#39;s around you and what you need to know. Peripheral visibility is the limiting factor - but to be honest, that often gets in the way of focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a driver&#39;s car. It&#39;s set up for you to get from A to B and to do so in comfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How does it drive?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It drives well. Very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model I&#39;ve driven is the single motor version with around 380kms of range. I had doubts about its performance based on the stats - but from a real-world perspective, it&#39;s everything it needs to be and a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&#39;t have the sickening acceleration of a Tesla or the dual-motor variants with a 4-point-something 0-100 speed - but it accelerates handsomely. What&#39;s great about this car is that the acceleration is available at any time - there&#39;s no lag, no gear change - push the accelerator, and there&#39;s instantly more power and speed. Driving through the Blue Mountains on the back roads was so much fun. Accelerating out of corners with instant speed was bliss. The car&#39;s handling was tight and responsive – it&#39;s an absolute joy to drive and throw around corners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This extends to the practical too - stop-start traffic, highway driving, handling broken roads and potholes - the Polestar does all of these things well. Really well. You&#39;re comfortable the whole time, and you&#39;re not freaking out about the drive in front because of the adaptive cruise control. The car doesn&#39;t shudder when you don&#39;t see the pothole or broken asphalt. The Polestar takes everything in its stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most electric vehicles have an energy recovery system or regenerative braking - a feature that uses the wheels to power the motor and recharge the battery. You don&#39;t get a huge amount of charge out of the process, but it is an interesting driving feature. It essentially provides the car with two ways to slow down: Use the wheels to power the motor and slow the wheels that way, or your standard brakes to slow the wheels down. This dynamic is one of the best features of an EV and creates the possibility of &lt;strong&gt;one-pedal drive&lt;/strong&gt; - similar to driving a Dodgem car – when you press the pedal, you go fast, and when you release, you slow down. You can still use the brake - but you can do most driving using one pedal. I loved this feature and have quickly converted to it. It&#39;s going to be a challenge going back to a normal car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took it out on a short gravel road and had quite an exciting experience using the one-pedal drive. Usually, on gravel, the car is searching for traction and slowing the car down with brakes to corner usually means losing traction. With the regenerative braking in the Polestar it essentially sucks the speed out of the car rather than physically braking, so taking corners was a genuinely strange experience. You don&#39;t lose traction slowing down and getting that noticeable drift, the only time you got that sense was when you accelerated back out of the corner. It was an added element to the driving experience and one I really liked, having done my fair share of backroads and dirt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the dual motor version would add that extra grunt and performance, this is not a car that is lacking in that department. The base model will accelerate faster, handle better and be more pleasant to drive than any family sedan. The battery range is adequate. It&#39;s not mind-blowing, but a big part of hiring this car was to look at how you would need to manage the content - and it&#39;s not a concern for most trips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Practicalities&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our hire car was the &lt;em&gt;standard range single motor&lt;/em&gt; with the &lt;em&gt;Pilot lite&lt;/em&gt; pack. You would want the Pilot pack as it has a range of features that really should be standard at this price point. The pack comes with a neat 360° camera feature, making parking easy. I always struggle with judging the distance behind and in front of the car, so this visual aid was perfect. The adaptive cruise control was also handy, especially in traffic. That sounds odd, using cruise control in the city, but the constant changes in sign-posted speed limits, traffic speed and the plethora of speed cameras and police on the roads make Sydney quite a combative place to drive. The cruise handled this easily, stopping at traffic lights and taking off once the light was green. The lane departure feature was quite aggressive, not something I would use often - except on the freeway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The car is a sedan, and the boot isn’t huge. It’s quite flat without a lot of height, so getting a suitcase in on its side (the most convenient) made the cover pop up and the boot unable to shut. It ended up being quite a Tetris challenge to get three suitcases in. It&#39;s not a dealbreaker and not something that would impact everyday use. There is ample space under the boot floor accessible via a lift-up section, but it is an odd shape. It became known as the “ham bay” as there was enough room for a whole leg of ham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Charging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key reasons for hiring the car was to assess the viability of owning an electric vehicle. What changes would you need to make to accommodate an electric vehicle and its need to charge?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carexpert.com.au/car-reviews/2022-polestar-2-long-range-single-motor-review&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.carexpert.com.au/crop/1600/1067/app/uploads/2021/11/Polestar-2518-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with — range anxiety is a very real thing. The car was at 100% charge when we picked it up, and I was quite nervous about how quickly that number decreased and the speed it did it. The first leg of our journey took us from Sydney airport down the coast to Jervis Bay. Rather than stick to the highway, we took a few of the backroads as we couldn’t check into our accommodation till 2pm. We used about half the battery that day - and the next couple of days I was a little worried at how things would go. There was no public charging infrastructure where we were staying - the nearest was 40 minutes drive away. That nervousness started to abate as time went on. We ran errands and visited the local sights without issue and made it to the public charger with 17% charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, range anxiety is very real – but it’s something you get over quite quickly. After that first charge I had much more confidence in the car, the range, and the accuracy of its own predictions. The built-in Google Maps has a button to search for chargers nearby. The maps are also scarily accurate with their predicted charge at the destination. So you can navigate with confidence using the car and know what charge you’ll have. I’m not sure if the Polestar app connects in the same way, allowing you to plot a journey away from the car - but that would be a great feature if it didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also downloaded and used the PlugShare app - checking in using it and seeing how useful a community-powered tool like this is, as well as the Evie app. Evie and Hertz have done a deal, and charges are free on Evie infrastructure via the RF card attached to the key fob.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big learning curves was finding out about the charging infrastructure - which varies quite significantly. The main difference between charging methods is speed - how much charge can go into the car.  My summary of what’s available is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wall plug - the car came with a wall plug cable, so we did two charges like this at the holiday house we were staying at.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charging plug - these outlets are significantly faster than your wall plug but need to be installed. They are often found at a location - like a supermarket, car park or some tourist destinations. They’re often free to use and pump out about 5kW.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purpose Charging - these are actual charging stations with a specifically designed installed and operate similarly to a petrol bowser. Pull up, use the in-built plug and charge away. These are commercial in nature, but at the moment, the NRMA in NSW have made them free, which I took advantage of in Berry. I also used an Evie station located at a shopping mall. Both advertised 50kW, but it seems variable about what you get into the car at the time - but I was getting about 35-45kW.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast Charging - similar to above but significantly faster and with higher output. I tried the Evie station at Seven Hills and was pumping in over 130kW into the car.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practically these options look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wall - About a day to charge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Didn’t use these - but I’m assuming they are useful for topping up a charge rather than “filling up”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over an hour to go from below 20% to between 80-90%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;32 minutes to go from 17% to 88%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Opinion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to divide this into two - one on the everyday use of an electric car, the other on the Polestar itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right here, today, I would 100% say yes to an electric car. I found the whole experience easy to manage, free of show-stopping issues and overall a really enjoyable driving experience An electric car is an amazing thing in so much as it’s just like driving a normal car - but &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; aspect of it is better. You can accelerate faster, slow down better, feel more in control of the car and lay down as much torque as you need when you need it. It’s an amazing feat of engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the Polestar. I love the look, and I love the drive, but I had a few practical issues with it. The centre console, for one, but also getting in and out of the car was a bit weird for a person with my height and dimensions. I felt like I should be stepping into the car, but it’s more like sliding across into it - and that’s just a bit weird. Everything else, though, I love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But… at the price point it’s at, there are a few more issues. The Pilot pack is extra, so to is the Plus pack to get all the creature comforts this car didn&#39;t come with. I would expect that if you were going to lay down this amount of money – they’d be included. They are in the Volvo XC40 Recharge, and they want less for it, and you get the dual motors. There’s also the brand new C40 - Volvo&#39;s first fully electric car platform, which is in the same price range. So from that perspective, it’s a hard sell to convince me to put down the money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said - if Polestar sharpened up their pricing, I would 100% rethink that opinion, but pricing for electric cars is their big issue at the moment. There are a few cheaper Chinese models coming in the next year - but most electric cars have a luxury price tag and they need to reflect that in their fit and features. I think Volvo get that - but Polestar’s pricing isn’t quite as good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if Polestar wants to get in touch and offer me a discount or wants a long-term tester - I would relish the opportunity. Going back to my &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; cars has taken quite a bit of adjustment. There&#39;s a lot I miss about the Polestar!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>