<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://heartsoulmachine.com/">
  <title>Heart Soul Machine</title>
  <subtitle>Posts from the blog of Tim Klapdor.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2023-09-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Tim Klapdor</name>
    <email>tim.klapdor@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Hello blog</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/09-26-hello-blog/"/>
    <updated>2023-09-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/09-26-hello-blog/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hey there blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while and I’ve been neglectful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life has been going on at a pace and with speed. Work has been crazy. As we discuss a University merger there’s been a reorganisation, a new team structure, the loss of an old team and a reprioritisation of work. Not at my choice or behest, but so it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve struggled with this round of changes, and I had to question myself about that. I feel like I’ve always been working on the edge of change, in that ambiguous state between new and old. If I’ve worked in the innovation space for so long, where I live and breathe change – why has this time been different? I think I understand it now, but it took a while to work through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large part of my experience has been around grief. A lot of what has happened has been the end of things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The team I originally joined is gone. We’ve been disbanded and repackaged beyond all recognition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The team I assembled anew and recruited for has also been changed beyond recognition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The manager who hired me went on to pursue something new and ended up leaving the institution completely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of the projects that I’ve been leading have finished – successful in their outcome but without acknowledgement or celebration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the work I’ve been doing hasn’t evolved in the way that I expected. I imagined riding the wave of developing these new online programs through to a more senior role. I poured a lot of myself, energy and time into that idea and outcome. But things haven’t worked out that way. Decisions have been made, or not, to pursue things in differently – one that doesn’t seem to include me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And my grief is connected to that. That loss of professional self, one that I’d been working so hard towards. From moving to a new city to working through the pandemic to going through the stress of hard deadlines and deliverables, to trying to manage the toll on my team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve wondered if the effort was worth it. I’ve played through the “What ifs?” I’ve asked myself why and come up blank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spawned grief over my effort and my time. I now acknowledge that there was a huge waste of effort. A lack of acknowledgement of what has been achieved has rubbed salt into the wound. The lack of recognition of the expertise I’ve spent years developing has been hurtful. Recognising that the organisation doesn’t care has been challenging. I’ve cared. I’ve probably cared too much. But the organisation doesn’t have feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 360° review demonstrated how little care there was. How little appreciation and recognition had been shown to all that work. I focused too much on getting things done that I didn’t see the impact that was having on me, or how others perceived me. From my team, peers and managers — I barely lived up to my own expectations, and I certainly didn’t see much recognition of what’s been achieved. But this is something I’ve been dealing with for a while – the invisibility of my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve felt frustrated at work for most of this year. Frustrated and ignored. When the future is a version of what I’ve just spent four years working on — I expected to be acknowledged and included in the decision-making. Instead, I was ignored. I get that not everyone has been on the same journey, but when you’ve been the pioneer, trailblazing and encountering all the ‘firsts’ – you’d think the organisation might want to hear about that. To learn from it. I guessed wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I fumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I smouldered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then it went out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That frustration just left one day. I accepted what was, and what had been, but now is different. I can make this what I want to be. Nothing has made it better. I don’t think anything has changed at all — except me. The one thing I can control and affect and change is me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s the aim. To stop doing what I was doing because it didn’t work. To look towards opportunities and to create my own. To embrace change again. What happens will happen, and regardless of how things have been perceived — I know the truth. I know what I did, what I achieved and what came out of those actions. Even if no one else can, I can see it and I’ve felt the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2023 - A Wrap</title>
    <link href="https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/01-31-2023-a-wrap/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://heartsoulmachine.com/blog/2023/01-31-2023-a-wrap/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;2023... WTF was that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year felt crazy. It felt like there were a lot more down points this year as plans and projections kept failing and falling over. A lot was happening at work, and that&#39;s where most of my energy was drawn into. There were a couple of  highlights though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fiji&lt;/strong&gt; - We had a great week in Fiji. There was a bit of drama, but it was such a good break during winter in a beautiful and friendly place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port Lincoln&lt;/strong&gt; - My wife and I headed to Port Lincoln to do the shark dive - jumping into a steel cage to see real-life Great White Sharks in their natural habitat. We saw four different sharks on the day! We spent the other days exploring the local area, the two national parks and some amazing sights and fresh seafood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Birthdays&lt;/strong&gt; - My mum&#39;s 70th and brother&#39;s 40th birthdays were this year. Mum&#39;s was a big family event and the first in a few years. It was great to see all the cousins and nieces all together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduation&lt;/strong&gt; - Seeing Ms A graduate from primary school. It&#39;s a much bigger deal than I remember, but it is a significant milestone for her and us as parents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a couple of work highlights too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colombia&lt;/strong&gt; - I gave an online presentation as part of the federal Department of Education &amp;amp; Training&#39;s initiative in South America. I did one last year for Brazil, so was aware of the bi-lingual nature of the event and what was involved. There were over 350 people in attendance on Zoom, which I was super impressed by.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ACODE LTLI&lt;/strong&gt; - A week in Queensland in August is never a bad thing. This institute was a lot of work and effort, though. It was great to get out of my bubble and meet a bunch of new people, as well as get to know my colleagues from Adelaide better during our downtime.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Change at work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was tremendous change at work, with the bulk of it starting in February and dragging out until August. I watched my career trajectory, or at least the way I imagined it going, crumble in front of my eyes. All the work I&#39;ve been doing over the last three years seemed to be leading to a specific point, and it seemed to be all on track. That all got completely derailed pretty early in the year, and I spent the rest of the year spinning. Rather than having leadership that steadied the ship and provided clear direction, we seemed to have the opposite — management keen on disruption for its own sake, an inability to communicate and unwillingness to engage their teams, under-baked ideas, no plans for operations and an obsession with adding more and more instability and momentum to the spiral and spin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;December has come, and my previous career path has disappeared in front of me. I&#39;ve felt increasingly angry, disrupted and troubled by this. I guess it is part of a grieving process, and I need to be comfortable with that being what has happened - grief. There was something clear and tangible that has taken away. There has been a loss, and it seems right to grieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t think I&#39;m alone in experiencing this, but it&#39;s probably the first time in my life I&#39;ve felt that I wasn&#39;t going in the right direction, not just in an upward direction but in general. Much of the effort I have put into things hasn&#39;t been rewarded or, honestly, even recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Knowledge Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my problem is making space for this grieving process to happen, to re-evaluate my position and make some decisions. One of the fundamental challenges of &lt;a href=&quot;https://heartsoulmachine.com/notes/knowledge-work/&quot;&gt;knowledge work&lt;/a&gt; is it involves your brain and thinking, which means making space and separating work and life is incredibly challenging. I found the two inexorably linked and that both were affecting each other. The problems at work bled into home life. The time needed to think ate into family time. I find this difficulty of knowledge work to be different from manual labour, especially when the job requires a machine or a specific location to do the work. Separation becomes easier if it is physical; there&#39;s a clear demarcation point in the day between work and family. At the end of this year I&#39;ve been completely exhausted all of the time. My brain is done and I haven&#39;t been there for my family or able to engage in the other pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the week off I&#39;ve had so far - I can see there needs to be some pretty fundamental changes in 2024. I want to spend the first few weeks of the year working through that. I have to really reevaluate this whole work/life balance concept, but the focus needs to be on &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crisis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve probably hit that midlife crisis point in terms of my career. I have started to ask myself that fundamental question — &lt;em&gt;what am I doing?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#39;t really enjoyed going to work this year. I don&#39;t think work should make you sad or angry. The culture has changed significantly over the last year and it hasn&#39;t made it a pleasant place to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said the people I work with and those that I have recruited into the team are amazing. One of the positives of the year has been the fact that I&#39;ve spent more time collaborating across teams and areas. That&#39;s been incredibly fulfilling and I honestly think if that hadn&#39;t happened this year would have felt a lot darker than it has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A new plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&#39;s time to evaluate where I am and where I am going. Luckily, I&#39;ve got time to do that over January as I&#39;ve taken four weeks off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming up to my 40th birthday, everything was looking good. We made a big change moving to Adelaide and taking on new jobs. Covid hit and that&#39;s had a much bigger effect on my life than I thought. There&#39;s a trauma that we&#39;ve gone through over the last few years that still hasn&#39;t been processed. So much changed - not just from the lockdowns, but how we interact, who we interact with and the confidence to get out there. Covid was such a big disruption and such a big traumatic event that life returning to normal really means now its normality wrapped around the trauma and isolation that occurred. It&#39;s not a return to &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; but &amp;quot;normal + trauma&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can feel now a deep need to connect. I don&#39;t think I&#39;ve spent a lot on the other things outside of work — individual pursuits, connection opportunities, socialising and networking. Work has been a leech on my energy and it&#39;s had a real parasitic effect on my wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, instead, I want to put effort into those spaces that give me energy and to seek out more joy and positivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s to 2024!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>